<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>R Submissions Working Group</title>
<link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.550</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-03-01</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-03-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (JBR) (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Nicholas Masel (JRDUS)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/_n7MWF0l4R5FsccL4GzRrzXUoGOCXwxQqQuY4Pu2CqF0_DX9xMmpYUoxREA92uX-.m3O3hPqvxfZKyws4?startTime=1709312595000">video</a> is available.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="plot-3-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plot-3-update">Plot 3 Update</h2>
<section id="fda-recommendation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fda-recommendation">FDA Recommendation</h3>
<p>HyeSoo stated that the FDA is considering issuing a recommendation that submissions sponsors should use the most recent patch version of the previous minor version of R.</p>
<p>For example, R versions are organized as V x.y.z where:</p>
<ul>
<li>x is the major version</li>
<li>y is the minor version or subversion</li>
<li>z is the patch version</li>
</ul>
<p>The WG members affirmed that a policy of using a proven stable version of R and not the latest version is in accordance with the practices of their respective companies.</p>
<p>After some thought the working group proposed that since patch versions are issued frequently (every couple of months), it might be better to have the FDA guidance suggest the last patch version of the previous subversion.</p>
<p>Note that the FDA is considering making a recommendation and not considering setting policy.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> JBR will confer with Sam, Paul and HyeSoo about the wording of the recommendation and then draft a blog post. The post will go to Paul, HyeSoo, Eric, and Ning for review before being published on the R Consortium Blog.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-update">Pilot 3 Update</h2>
<p>HyeSoo and Joel informed the group that they met last month to resolve the discrepancy between the original CDISC version of the ADADAS ADaM data set and the Pilot 3 version of the ADaM data set. Joel noted that there are 818 available records in the QS domain. The CDISC ADADAS only brought in 799 records and imputed the rest, whereas Pilot 3 brought in all available 818 records into ADADAS and then imputed. When the Pilot 3 team adjusted by subsetting to ANL01FL=‘Y’ records first before doing the LOCF imputation the results matched Pilot 1 and the discrepancy was resolved. Look <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam/pull/146">here</a> for details.</p>
<p>This issue illustrates the level of detail that the FDA must consider in replicating a sponsor’s submission environment. This particular issue was due to a statistical decision and not an error. Ning pointed out that most of the work in resolving discrepancies over the three Pilot submissions are due to insufficient documentation and inadequate communication and not to differences between SAS and R.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> Ning and Joe will work on a blog post about this topic.</p>
</section>
<section id="rmedicine" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rmedicine">R/Medicine</h2>
<p>Joel has been invited to give a talk at the upcoming R/Medicine virtual conference which will be held from June 10 to 14. He is deciding whether to give a talk or a workshop.</p>
</section>
<section id="user-2024" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="user-2024">UseR! 2024</h2>
<p>The group decided to submit an abstract for useR!2024 which will be held from July 8 to 11 in Salzburg, Austria. the deadline for the CFP is Sunday, 10 March at 11:59 PM CET (UTC+1)</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<p>Eric and Ning will draft the abstract.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-update">Pilot 4 update</h2>
<p>At <strong>38:38</strong> into the video of the meeting, Eric previews the Pilot 4 WebAssembly (Wasm) submission. To be compatible with Wasm, the submission is being built with the <a href="https://appsilon.github.io/rhino/">Rhino</a> framework for shiny which is different from what was used in Pilot 2 but is functionally equivalent. The screen capture below references the compiling the <code>WebR</code> Wasm submission with <code>shinylive</code>.</p>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-03-01/pilot4.png" class="img-fluid"> After the build it is necessary to launch a webserver process on your your local setup. The Wasm version of the Shiny app reproduces the <code>teal</code> filters without using teal itself.</p>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-03-01/KM.png" class="img-fluid"> The next step is to test the application on the container approximating the FDA Windows environment.</p>
<section id="immediate-plans" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="immediate-plans">Immediate Plans</h3>
<p>Joel’s team will continue working on Pilot 3 re-submission with the goal of picking a submission date at the April meeting.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-submission-environmnt-setup" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-submission-environmnt-setup">The Submission Environmnt Setup</h2>
<p>Setting up the submission environment is a manual process. The WG would like to automate at lest some of this process to ease the burden of setup and improve repeatability. It would be nice to have a GitHub action workflow that uses containers and runs on Azure. This will be a topic for the next meeting.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> JBR will promote this task and try to find a company willing to work on it.</p>
</section>
<section id="swissmedic-wg" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="swissmedic-wg">Swissmedic WG</h2>
<p>JBR asked the WG for help in identifying Europe-based Pharma employees who might be interested in starting a new working group focused on Swissmedic.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> Ning will open an issue on this and tag JBR and Gregory.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-meeting">Next Meeting</h2>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be on Friday, April 5, 2024 at 9AM PST.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-03-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-02-02</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-02-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Eva Li</li>
<li>Gregory Chen (MSD)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Kaushal Shah (ASU)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/dtAH375BZFxiI7SK8H5aciRvsd-8YSpCoNiUduKf9xppCitN80J2N2fZrG6A6m4V.g0LkTMFG35sCXuXj?startTime=1706893431000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h2>
<p>Hye Soo Cho presented a summary of the findings of the from the FDA review</p>
<ul>
<li>Different versions of R and RStudio
<ul>
<li>There were issues switching between R versions</li>
<li>The FDA would like the wg to explore the impact of different versions of R,RStudio and RTools</li>
<li>Also Linux vs.&nbsp;Windows</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Differences between generated Pilot 2 ADaM and CDISC data sets
<ul>
<li>attributes</li>
<li>types (e.g.&nbsp;integer vs.&nbsp;double)</li>
<li>NA vs.&nbsp;NULL</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Package and file names
<ul>
<li>Incorrect package name (pilot3utils)</li>
<li>File name change (Pilot 3.xlsx to adam-pilot-3.xlsx)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>File path
<ul>
<li>The location of a director was specified using relative file path</li>
<li>Recommendation: use full path name</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Different primary output in Pilot 1 and Pilot 3
<ul>
<li>There are discrepancies between Pilot 3 ADaM and CDISC datasets</li>
<li>Discrepancies are noted in QC findings in ADRG</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>There was considerable discussion about the challenges of dealing with different R versions and establishing a Windows test environment to test a submission before transmitting it to the FDA.</p>
<ul>
<li>The idea of setting up a gold standard windows test environment was considered but reject as beginning impractical. The actual FDA environment changes frequently because of hot fixes addressing security concerns.</li>
<li>It appears that the most practical path forward as to what preemptive measures sponsors can take to match submission environments with the FDA test environment is to work with the FDA to lock down the environment as best as can be done just prior to submission.</li>
<li>An interesting note: Paul mentioned that the FDA no longer pushes the idea of last observation carried forward for imputations. They favor exploring multiple imputation methods.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Actions:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The FDA will consider the implications of what was discussed today and decide if we are ready to resubmit Pilot 3 by the next meeting in March. The submission will use the .zip approach.</li>
<li>Joel agreed to speak with Eric about establishing an automated way to set up a container running a “vanilla” Windows test environment. <strong>Note:</strong> in a series of private email conversations after the meeting Robert Devine volunteered his expertise to work with Eric and Joel to set up the windows environment.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<p>Eric provided a brief update on Pilot 4.</p>
<ul>
<li>He will convene the Pilot 4 team to test the Webassembly submission,</li>
<li>The submission should be ready by mid March.</li>
<li>We will decide on an actual submission date in March.</li>
<li>Eric will invite the Appsilon engineers who have be providing assistance on the project to one of our meetings as we get closer to the submission.</li>
<li>The container version of the Pilot 4 submission will coordinate with the FDA to make arrangements for working with containers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="presentation-to-swiss-medic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="presentation-to-swiss-medic">Presentation to Swiss Medic</h2>
<p>On January 30, Gregory Chen presented the activities of our working group in person to an audience 15 people at the <a href="https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/en/home.html">swissmedic</a> regulatory agency and 50 people online. Gregory’s slides are in the <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-wg/tree/main/_Documents">github repository</a>. He summarized the discussion that took place after his presentation.</p>
<ul>
<li>The swissmedic audience was very interested in the use of Shiny for the Pilot 2 submission and would like to work with the R Consortium to explore the possibility of doing something similar at swissmedic. They discussed two possible ways to proceed:
<ol type="1">
<li>A Pilot 2 like project</li>
<li>Having sponsors set up a cloud environment</li>
</ol></li>
<li>The swissmedic audience said that they would prefer an industry collaborative effort rather than a vendor specific solution.</li>
<li>The were interested in learning about the resources the FDA allocated to the Pilot 2 and * asked about creating Shiny applications for market authorization.</li>
<li>The WG was excited about the possibility of collaborating with swissmedic</li>
<li>However, after some discussion it was decided that this opportunity should be pursued by a new working group devoted to swissmedic.</li>
<li>We should also find out if swissmedic has discussed these ideas with the EMA.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>JBR will work figure out how best to recruit members for a new working group focused on swissmedic.</li>
<li>This should include a call to the industry to identify people with European connections who could lead this effort.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM PST on Friday, March 1, 2024,</p>
<section id="abstract-for-gregorys-presentation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract-for-gregorys-presentation">Abstract for Gregory’s Presentation</h3>
<p><u>Name of presenter</u>: Gregory Chen</p>
<p><u>Affiliation</u>: MSD, Switzerland; R Submission Working group (R Consortium)</p>
<p><u>Brief introduction of the working group</u>:</p>
<p>The R submission working group is a cross-industry working group in pharma, focusing on improving practices of R-based clinical trial regulatory submissions. Our mission is to make R-based clinical trial regulatory submissions easier today and tomorrow by</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>showing open examples of using current submission portals,</p></li>
<li><p>collecting feedback and influencing future industry and agency decisions on system/process setup</p></li>
</ol>
<p><u>Title</u>: R and Shiny in regulatory submission</p>
<p><u>Abstract</u>:</p>
<p>In recent years, statisticians and analysts from both industry and regulatory agencies have increased adoption of open-source software such as R. Compared to other statistical programming languages, R brought great benefit from its vibrant open-source community, providing a wealth of cutting-edge statistical tools and adaptability to the latest data science trends. Particularly, R shiny provided great flexibility and interactivity to increase data scientists productivity and make it easier to extract insights or review through massive statistical outputs.&nbsp;To test the concept that R language and shiny app can be bundled into a submission package and transferred successfully to FDA reviewers, the R Submission Working group (R Consortium) successfully completed two pilot submissions to FDA fully in R, and received CDER response letters (<a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/blog/2021/12/08/successful-r-based-test-package-submitted-to-fda">pilot 1,</a> <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/announcement/2023/10/05/shiny-app-successfully-reviewed-by-fda-cder-staff-pilot-2-announcement-2">pilot 2</a>). To our knowledge, these are the first publicly available submission packages that include components of open-source languages. In this talk, we will introduce R consortium, particularly its Submission Working group, and the completed pilot 1 and 2.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-02-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-01-05</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-01-05/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</li>
<li>Eva Li</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Margaret Wishart</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Steven Hasendinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/S3CjidPqOBSwSHo7xW3VUu_aUXKS9RdB3rNb07hWWkeyze5SthawUq5I8gnzQ2th.kpiljMfkqrlkuUJf?startTime=1704474237000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h2>
<p>HyeSoo presented an update on the continuing FDA evaluation of Pilot 3.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Using the R generated ADaM data sets, the FDA reviewers were able to replicate the results of the demographic, efficacy, primary and KM plot analyses</p></li>
<li><p>The reviewers compared the results of the four analyses between Pilot 1 and Pilot 3.</p>
<ul>
<li>Primary output in Pilot 3 was different from the Pilot 1 result due to the QC findings</li>
<li>QC findings in ADRG include all of the discrepancies between the original ADaM datasets</li>
<li>The discrepancies in ADADAS data sets cause different primary analyses outputs</li>
<li>This is an issue from the CDISC ADADAS</li>
<li>It is not clear which CDISC file, the file from Pilot 1 or the file from Pilot 3, is correct.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>The following figure compares the Pilot 1 and Pilot 3 primary output. Discrepancies are highlighted.</p>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-01-05/output_compare.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Comparison of Primary outputs"> Additional FDA questions included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Why is there an indication in the output of LOCF, “Last observation carried forward” when the original data set had no missing data?</li>
<li>There was no statistical analysis plan included in the submission.</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> Ben Straub will confer with the Pilot 3 team to answer these questions and review the discrepancy problems between Pilots 1 and 3.</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> Paul and HyeSoo will discuss whether we need to resubmit Pilot 3 The next meeting of the working group will be on Friday, February 2, 2024 at 9AM Pacific Time.</li>
<li>All agreed that if a resubmission of Pilot 3 is required, we will consider submitting via a .zip file.</li>
</ul>
<p>There was some discussion about what we could do to improve the quality control of our submissions.</p>
<ul>
<li>The group agreed that we should have a check list to compare items against a Pilot 1 source of truth.</li>
<li>We should have additional reviewers who are not close to the work.</li>
<li>The idea of using AI tools to check consistency was mentioned.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming-webinar" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming-webinar">Upcoming Webinar</h2>
<p>On Monday at 7PM PST Rikimaru Nishimura and Yuki Matsunaga will present a webinar on The Adoption of R in Japan’s Pharma Industry Confirmation. Look <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/r-adoption-series-the-adoption-of-r-in-japans-pharma-industry-confirmation">here</a> for details and information on how to register.</p>
<ul>
<li>Ning noted that Yuki expressed an interest in collaborating with the R Consortium.</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> we will set up a meeting with the Japanese team after the meeting.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pharmasug" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pharmasug">PharmaSUG</h2>
<ul>
<li>JBR mentioned that it is an R Consortium goal for 2024 to make the opportunity for as many speaking engagements as possible.</li>
<li>Ben mentioned that <a href="https://www.pharmasug.org/us/index.html">PharmaSUG 2024</a> is coming up in May,</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> Ben volunteered to submit an abstract by the January 15 deadline. Ning will provide Ben with some copy used for a previous abstract.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM PST on Friday, February 2, 2024.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-01-05/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-12-01</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-12-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>YounKyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Steven Hasendinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and screen sharing in the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/rE68tBPpnjdwl0RhevCYKDzq-FA7Z0kla1dSbHixZXZ9jHzoe4Kud-6Mc3r4-PKd.25fRPYZYgN0MzxxU?startTime=1701450234000">video</a> provides information about the FDA review of Pilot 3 which is in progress.</p>
<p>JBR began the meeting the meeting with a reminder that the meeting is to be conducted in compliance with the Antitrust laws.</p>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<p>YounKyeong Chang of the FDA provided and update on he ongoing FDA review.</p>
<ul>
<li>Able to generate identical data sets with the code provided, but there were some minor corrections and issues.</li>
<li>Incorrect folder name in adlvc.r</li>
<li>After switching to R.4.2.3, code in ADRG installed pilotutils package instead of pilot3 package. Switching to from R 4.3.1 to R 4.2.3 resolved the problem.</li>
<li>There was an extensive discussion about missing values.</li>
<li>The CDISC standard indicates missing values with blanks, and depending on the variable type SAS may also use blanks for missing values. However, R encodes missing values as “NA”.</li>
<li>Decision made to convert missing values to NA when using R, but provide an option to use blanks for analysts using SAS. However, the FDA does not yet have an SOP for this.</li>
<li>A paragraph will be added to the ADRG to explain that SAS users should convert NAs to blanks.</li>
<li>The ADaM datasets in Pilot 3 where run through <a href="https://www.lexjansen.com/pharmasug/2019/DS/PharmaSUG-2019-DS-119.pdf">Pinnacle 21</a> without error.</li>
<li>the WG should reach out to CDISC to see if they will modify their standard to accommodate R.</li>
<li><strong>Action</strong> Ning and Joel will prepare a statement to communicate with CDISC.</li>
<li>Sharing of the details of any FDA findings, such as as those discussed in the meeting, require clearance</li>
<li>Some minor differences were observed in how SAS and R interpreted data types.</li>
<li>The FDA will try to evaluate the submission outputs by next month’s meeting</li>
<li>The WG agreed that after the evaluation of Pilot 3 is completed, it would be interesting to do a Pilot 3B submission using .zip instead of <code>pkglite</code> as was used in Pilots 1 and 2. Paul said that in light of the FDA requirement to keep submission materials for 6 years this would provide an alternative for long term preservation of the submission materials.</li>
<li>The FDA will make a decision whether an additional Pilot 3 submission to correct the problems identified so far is necessary after they have completed their evaluation.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<p>Eric Nantz provide a status update on Pilot 4</p>
<ul>
<li>Pilot 4 will take the approach of submitting as a .zip archive.</li>
<li>An issue is that the default behavior of <code>WebR</code> is to install a special version of some commonly used R packages that are optimized for <code>WebR</code>.</li>
<li>We would like to include these special <code>WebR</code> binaries in the submission bundle in order to improve performance.</li>
<li>Because the binaries are not executable without a WebAssembly process running, the WG believes these binaries wold not violate the FDA requirement of not including executables.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="events" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="events">Events</h3>
<ul>
<li>Eric, Hyesoo, and Paul will be presenting on December 11 in a Webinar that will be broadcast within the FDA as well as available to the public. Ning will lead a panel discussion afterwards.</li>
<li>The webinar <em>The use of R in Japan’s Pharma Industry</em> is scheduled for January 8, 2024.</li>
<li>Gregory Chen will be presenting the WGs work in person at Department of Clinical Assessment for Market Authorization at Swiss medic in January</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting will take place at 9AM St on Friday, January 5, 2025. <strong>Action:</strong> JBR will issue a new set of calendar invitations for 2024. Stay tuned for details.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-12-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-11-03</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-11-03/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Minutes prepared by Joseph Rickert and Joel Laxamana.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Kaushal Shah</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (ProCogia)</li>
<li>Ismael Alejandro Rodriguez Rodriguez (Appsilon)</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang (Meta)</li>
<li>YounKyeong Chang</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/5kFrV4r2DWK1aHHozPu0k8fu_66jV4IRlVsWoEgrnyocLF8ki-KBswB6wBEcBQmm.-txYArp2uGa7KpZp?startTime=1699027425000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="fdasa-presentation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fdasa-presentation">FDASA Presentation</h3>
<ul>
<li>The FDASA would like to invite the R Consortium to present at their meeting on December 11, 2023 (3 to 4:30PM ET).</li>
<li>However the FDASA would like to extend an informal invitation rather than formally sponsor the event which would require administrative approvals</li>
<li>The RC would still be able to advertise that Paul and HyeSoo are speaking</li>
<li>The RC would conduct the event which is expected to attract at least 200 of the approximately 400 FDASA participants.</li>
<li>Registration of the event is not required</li>
<li>The RC can also invite the general public to attend. (JBR will confer with Ning and Eric about doing this.)</li>
<li>JBR will s=send an invitation to the event, which should include the abstract, to Paul to be used to invite FDASA members to the event through internal channels.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<p>HeySoo and Paul provide some preliminary comments regarding their evaluation of Pilot 3. An extensive discussion starts approximately 12 minutes into the video recording.</p>
<ul>
<li>The ADRG states that Pilot 3 was uses R 4.2.3. However, FDA may test using different R versions. (i.e.&nbsp;one reviewer using Rv4.2.1 and other using Rv4.2.3). There are at least two kinds of workstations used by FDA reviewers. Reviewers with “scientific workstations” may have administrative privileges and be able to install R. Users on other “regulatory” workstations will most likely use the version of R installed by IT.</li>
<li>The Pilot 3 package didn’t install using renv::install() when using Rv4.2.1, but did install when the reviewer was using Rv4.2.3.</li>
<li>The submissions programs which process ADaM data were not updated to match the file adam-pilot-3.xlsx which was included in the submission.</li>
<li>Reviewers were able to update the file name. When they did so the adsl.r ran fine.</li>
<li>Do not include notes to change the path to source data file in the ADRG steps. Instead, keep a note open to advise reviewers that they “should change the source data path to the location where the data was downloaded from the EDR”.</li>
<li>The submission documentation should include the version of the Microsoft operating system used along with the the version of the RStudio IDE used.</li>
<li>Sponsors using proprietary software also encounter Operating system issues. There may also be issues with respect to a difference in the size and power of the computers used by the sponsors and those available to the FDA reviewers.</li>
<li>There may be problems if file names using upper case letters are used in submissions. The FDA technical conformance guide specifies the use of lower case letters.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the Submissions WG will be held at 9AM Pacific Time on Friday, December 8, 2023.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-11-03/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-10-06</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-10-06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Andrew Borgman (Bristol Myers Squibb)</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Kaushal Shah (ASU)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/3VPBIvULy8dJcVRBngyPKjgxOrLNFFJ4zIPI8seYpBoOk1LFzNEYd6BxyoPWiwjc.aOV0PJIel6jPMV68?startTime=1696608150000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="new-member" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-member">New Member</h3>
<p>HyeSoo introduced Youn Kyeong Chang as a new member of the group who will be helping to evaluate the pilot submissions for the FDA.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<ul>
<li>JBR began the meeting by noting the successful conclusion of the <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/announcement/2023/10/05/shiny-app-successfully-reviewed-by-fda-cder-staff-pilot-2-announcement-2">Pilot 2 submission</a> and commenting on the attention it is getting throughout the industry.</li>
<li>The group thanked Paul and HyeSoo for there work on the project and their efforts to shepherd the review through the FDA process.</li>
<li>Ning remarked that it was really helpful that Paul was able to provide us with the FDA letter for the ASA conference.</li>
<li>Ning and Eric talked about the how much attention their poster got at the conference.</li>
<li>The working group is enthusiastic about doing an R Consortium webinar about the Pilot 2 project.</li>
<li>The tentative date for the webinar is 3:00PM EST on Monday December 11, 2023.</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> Ning will prepare the letter requesting speakers for the FDA and contact the R Adoption series organizers.</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> JBR will also contact the R Consortium webinar production team.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<ul>
<li>HyeSoo laid out a timeline for evaluating Pilot 3, saying it would take an additional six to seven months to complete.</li>
<li>Ben said that there is quite a bit of interest at GSK about the ADRG because Pilot 3 did not use pkglite.</li>
<li>HyeSoo remarked that the ADRG is different but that her preliminary look did not show any problems.</li>
<li>There was some discussion abut looking back at the ADRGs made for both Pilot 2 and Pilot 3.</li>
<li>Eric noted that he made the Pilot 2 ADRG in Quarto and was very happy with the workflow.</li>
<li>We can expect feedback on the review during our normal sessions.</li>
<li>Ben Staub noted that Novo Nordisk about presentation about their recent R submission.</li>
<li>Paul remarked that he cannot comment on the Novo Nordisk submission since it is not finalized, but he did say that what Novo Nordisk said in their presentation about keeping things simple (limiting packages and dependencies) and being able to trace key endpoints is the same advice the FDA would be give.</li>
<li>Paul also noted that the fact that the FDA is not able to comment on submissions in progress is one reason why it is nice to have a pilot.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<ul>
<li>Eric reported that he had the opportunity with meet with the Appsilon folks helping with Pilot 4 at posit::conf and that next sprint on the project will begin this coming week.</li>
<li>JBR brought up on several limitations to WebAssembly, such as not being able to accommodate networking functions in the browser.</li>
<li>Eric replied that Pilot 4 is not likely to hit the constraining limits, but that these may become a concern as we move into more robust submissions in 2024. (This discussion begins about 21:00 in the video)</li>
<li>JBR asks that we take the trouble to communicate clearly about our knowledge of the limitations.</li>
<li>There was a discussion about whether the FDA would be ready to receive a container based sub-submission.</li>
<li>The agreed that Pilot 4 in two parts: part a will be WebAssembly based and part b sill be based on containers.</li>
<li>Eric believes that he will be ready to submit Part 4.a in mid December. Paul will confer with his management about resources being available in that time frame.</li>
<li>There was a discussion about whether setting up a server with containers outside of the FDA would we be helpful for FDA reviewers becoming familiar with Podman.</li>
<li>JBR remarked that other working groups are interested in establishing protocols, best practices, and requirements for repositories.</li>
<li>Paul noted that from the FDA’s point of view, longevity should be a requirement noting that 6 years would be a minimum and there may be reasons to consider 20 years.</li>
<li>The group decided that it would be feasible and may be helpful to set up a server with the Pilot 2 submission shiny app running in a container.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="participation-in-the-isbs-7th-symposium" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="participation-in-the-isbs-7th-symposium">Participation in the ISBS 7th Symposium</h3>
<ul>
<li>JBR mentioned that he received an an invitation from Qi, Hong <a href="mailto:hong_qi@merck.com" class="email">hong_qi@merck.com</a>, the organizer of the <a href="https://www.isbiostat.org/">The 7th International Symposium on Biopharmaceutical Statistics</a> to present a 20 minute talk at the event. The invitation is below.</li>
<li>Link to <a href="https://www2.aeplan.co.jp/isbs2019/invited.html">ISBS past event</a></li>
<li>The group agreed that we should try to participate even though it seems to be a primarily statistician driven event.</li>
<li>Ning offered to put together an abstract.</li>
<li>Pending some final investigation, JBR will let them know that we would like to participate but that we do not yet know who the speaker will be.</li>
<li>JBR noted that it might be an opportunity to present the FDA’s view about the kind of statistics and principles that govern an FDA submission.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="fdasa-proposal" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fdasa-proposal">FDASA Proposal</h3>
<ul>
<li>Ning has prepared a final version of the abstract for a session solely from the R Consortium.</li>
<li>Joe will send the proposal in a with a cover letter to Paul.</li>
<li>The ASA Biopharma working group intends to send its own proposal for a talk.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM PST on Friday November 3, 2023.</p>
</section>
<section id="invitation-from-isbs" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="invitation-from-isbs">Invitation from ISBS</h3>
<p>Dear Joseph,</p>
<p>Thanks so much for expressing interest in presenting at The 7th International Symposium on Biopharmaceutical Statistics, which will take place on March 6 – 9, 2024, at Hilton Baltimore Inner Harbor. The symposium is organized by the International Society for Biopharmaceutical Statistics (ISBS). Prominent statisticians and drug development professionals from regulatory agencies, academia, and industry will deliver keynote speeches on various emerging/evolving fields. Invited and contributed presentations will cover a wide range of topics including innovative statistics, clinical development, regulatory science, and data science.</p>
<p>We are organizing a Regulatory Submission session dedicated to communicating the agencies’ requirements for drug submission, and the implementation of industry standards to support the acquisition, exchange, analysis, submission and archival of clinical data and metadata in the pharmaceutical industry. We cordially invite you to present an R topic related to regulatory submission. Each presentation has 20 minutes including speech and Q&amp;A. It is highly appreciated if you may provide the presentation topic and presenter(s)’ name by October 15, 2023. Below are the important dates:</p>
<p>Abstract submission due: Oct.&nbsp;29th, 2023. Registration start date: Nov.&nbsp;15th, 2023. Presentation slides due: Feb.&nbsp;15th, 2024. Sincerely,</p>
<p>Mary Varughese, Chair Hong Qi, Organizer</p>
<p>Regulatory Submission Session</p>
<p>7th Symposium, ISBS</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-10-06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-09-01</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-09-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/nG5RS852RTgvfz3wYmQzX-Wfei82ZlkfvaNd3UpqbeMHbvVqdYKHEwjc3VinIQ.7-hyNhzzPESRq00r?startTime=1693584254000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<p>Paul Schuette provided and update on the Agency’s review of Pilot 2</p>
<ul>
<li>HyeSoo Cho completed her review and passed it on to FDA authorities for additional review.</li>
<li>Paul feels that he and HyeSoo anticipate they will be able to answer any questions from the reviewers</li>
<li>Paul does not anticipate problems</li>
<li>It may take two weeks or longer to close things out</li>
<li>Paul will include some material about Pilot 1 in his up coming ASA data set</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Actions:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Joel will send Paul the data set link used for Pilot 1</li>
<li>Joel will review the draft announcement for Pilot 3, Ning will approve and pass it to Paul for his review.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<p>Joel Laxamana provided the status update.</p>
<ul>
<li>Did not use <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=pkglite">pkglite</a></li>
<li>submitted the .r file</li>
<li>Installed proprietary package from its own repo</li>
<li>Had to change .lock file to renv-lock.txt and provide instructions how to change it back.</li>
<li>Team members tested on Linux, Mac, and Windows</li>
<li>Submitted the Pilot through the FDA gateway</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho, the FDA Pilot 3 reviewer, contacted the FDA gateway team to request access and expects to receive access next week</li>
<li>HyeSoo believes she will be able to report on Pilot 3 by the October meeting.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<p>Eric Nantz provided a status up date on Pilot 4 describing the significant progress that has been made with developing prototypes for both the WebAssemply and Container approaches.</p>
<section id="webassembly" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="webassembly">WebAssembly</h4>
<ul>
<li>At 19:48 minutes in to the video Eric displays the Pilot 4 teams minutes for their recent meeting, <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot4/minutes/2023-08-18/">Minutes 2023-08-18</a>, and talks through the activities.</li>
<li>George Stagg and Winston Chang from Posit attended the Pilot 4 meeting</li>
<li>The <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=httpuv">httpuv</a> R package will be necessary to start up a mini web server in the user’s local environment. There will be a script to accomplish this.</li>
<li>There will be no traces of the Shiny app interacting with the host system</li>
<li>Binaries of the packages used will be included in the transfer. These will not be executable binaries. They will be similar to .tar or .zip files.</li>
<li>The end user will have to install the version of R used in Pilot 1</li>
<li><a href="https://shiny.posit.co/py/docs/shinylive.html">Shinylive</a> is another rapidly developing technology that may per pertinent to Pilot 4. Currently Shinylive is only available for Python. However, Winston Chang expects the R based version will be available soon.</li>
<li>Eric demos Shinylive from the posit website at 28:00 minutes into the video</li>
<li>See the Posit post <a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2023/08/webr-0-2-0/">webR 0.2.0</a> for additional information.</li>
<li>A Pilot 4 submission based on WebAssembly technology looks feasible by the end of the year.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="containers" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="containers">Containers</h4>
<ul>
<li>Eric’s team already has a Podman container with Pilot 2 running</li>
<li>The team is waiting for Paul to clarify what is required by the FDA IT team for them be able to receive containers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="preferred-technology" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="preferred-technology">Preferred technology</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the WebAssembly version does not require the involvement of FDA technology, it looks like it is the preferred method for a first Pilot 4 submission</li>
<li>At 37:43 minutes into the video, Eric shows the “Hello World” version of a WebAssembly submission created by Appsilon engineers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="promotion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="promotion">Promotion</h3>
<ul>
<li>Joseph Rickert suggests that the story of the Submissions group cooperative effort is as important as the story of the technology.</li>
<li>The story of the overall submission group should be written up, However, Joe proposed that since the Pilot 4 effort is moving so quickly and involves contributions not only from working group members, but also from vendors we should tell this story first while the details are fresh.</li>
<li>Eric agrees that the participation of the two development teams from Posit and Appsilon is unique.</li>
<li>Eric notes that he has submitted a talk about Pilot 4 for the R/Pharma conference</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Eric and Ning will update the GitHub sites for the Pilot teams to make sure the information is up to date and all the contributors are recognized.</li>
<li>Eric, Joe, Eric agree to work on an end of year thank you / celebration post.</li>
<li>Joe will make sure the R Consortium promotes Eric’s talk</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="novo-nordisk-submission" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="novo-nordisk-submission">Novo Nordisk Submission</h3>
<ul>
<li>Joe asked the group if anyone has information about the Novo Nordisk all R submission.</li>
<li>See the upcoming <a href="https://posit.co/blog/novo-nordisks-journey-to-an-r-based-fda-submission/">webinar</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM PST on Friday October 6, 2023.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-09-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-08-04</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-08-04/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Li Eva</li>
<li>Christopher Kania (Biogen)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Shannon Lewis (BeiGene)</li>
<li>Stephanie Lussier (Moderna)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="minutes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minutes">Minutes</h2>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/iap2ryh7-PHu8_fOMfwtXHpO7D7hB333mCsNODLlxE99EoCGXRTm1MSEFP7ceXzk.DnZSMt89C-TB8tZj?startTime=1691165275000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<ul>
<li>HyeSoo Cho reported that she is working with the Pilot 2 re-submission and that it looks good.</li>
<li>HyeSoo expects that the final on this pilot submission will be available at the end of August.</li>
<li>Everyone recognized and thanked Eric Nantz for the sustained and last-minute efforts to get the submission out.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<ul>
<li>Paul Schuette brought the attention of the group to section 4.i.2.10 of the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/study-data-technical-conformance-guide-technical-specifications-document">Study Data Technical Conformance Guide - Technical Specification Document</a> and noted that .r and .zip files are listed as acceptable file formats for submissions.</li>
<li>After some discussion, the WG decided not to use <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=pkglite">pkglite</a> to wrap the R code as has been done in previous submissions, but to use .r files for the code. (Note that the FDA is unable to use .R internally.)</li>
<li>Paul noted that the FDA desires submission materials to be applicable for at least six years after submission. This triggered a discussion about possibility of using .zip files to transmit the proprietary packages, instead of pulling them from public GitHub repos as been done so far.</li>
<li>In the end, the WG decided to stick with using GitHub repos for Pilot 3 as there is currently no apparent advantage testing the .zip file method at this time.</li>
<li>Joel Laxama reported that preparations for Pilot 3 are going well, and that a submission using .r files could be made in early September.</li>
<li>The WG thought it best to wait for the report of Pilot 2 before submitting Pilot 3.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<ul>
<li>Eric reported that thanks to the contributions form the <a href="https://appsilon.com/">Appsilon</a> team significant progress has been made on using both mechanisms for packaging R submissions: Containers and <a href="https://webassembly.org/">Webassembly</a>.</li>
<li>Appsilon has a prototype submission using <a href="https://podman.io/">Podman</a> container technology working and has confirmed that it does not cause files to be written to the hard-drive.</li>
<li>Eric and the Appsilon engineers also have a very preliminary prototype of using Webassembly to wrap a small Shiny app working.</li>
<li>Posit engineers have contributed <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=webr">webr</a> expertise.</li>
<li>Eric is optimistic about having Pilot submissions based on at least one, and possibly both, of these technologies ready by the end of the year.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Paul will confer with the proper FDA authorities to determine what preparations need to be undertaken by the FDA to use the Podman containers.</li>
<li>Eric will invite an Appsilon representative to come to a future meeting of this working group</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="july-21-san-jose-state-r-foundation-event" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="july-21-san-jose-state-r-foundation-event">July 21 San Jose State R Foundation Event</h3>
<p>The R Foundation <a href="https://bbsw-tickets.ticketleap.com/summer-r-day2/">SummeR Bay Area R Meetup</a> was held at San Jose State University on July 21. Ning Leng reports that:</p>
<ul>
<li>The 50 plus attendees indicated that quite a few Bay Area companies are moving towards using R in preclinical and genomics research.</li>
<li>Representatives from several small CROs attended the meeting.</li>
<li>R Consortium recognition was not good among this group.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>JBR and Ning to discuss what can be done to promote the RC.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="speaking-opportunities" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speaking-opportunities">Speaking Opportunities</h3>
<ul>
<li>Eric will submit an abstract to speak about Pilot 3 and Pilot 4 at the <a href="https://bbsw-tickets.ticketleap.com/summer-r-day2/">R/Pharma</a> virtual conference to be held in on October 24 - 26.</li>
<li>Paul will be presenting at both at the <a href="https://advance.phuse.global/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=70778947">PHUSE/FDA CSS 2023</a> conference on September 18 -20 and the <a href="https://advance.phuse.global/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=70778947">ASA Biopharmaaceutical Section Regulatory-Industry statistics Workshop</a> to be held in Rockville, MD on September 27 - 29 and intends to use the activities of this working group as a case study.</li>
<li>Ning suggests that it would be very nice if the RC could hold and R Adoption Webinar in the November time frame to describe the Pilot 2 and Pilot 3 submissions.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Paul will check with FDA authorities to see whether it is appropriate for the R Consortium to publicize his speaking opportunities on social media.</li>
<li>JBR will work with the RC Community development committee to make preparations for the promoting the speaking activities and setting up the webinar.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the Submissions working group will be at 9AM PST on Friday, September 1st.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-08-04/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-07-07</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-07-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang (Meta)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="add-minutes-here" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="add-minutes-here">Add Minutes Here</h2>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/UWy0e4rQiG-Qa7LJL8NT6cLCrl0PgqZPr93VAVBZowYbCnqZ01C1hQDf1haXAdM_.n__f-SUm5BcNMzgm?startTime=1688745965000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<p>Eric Nantz has made progress on addressing the issues identified with the Pilot 2 resubmission. Fixes include:</p>
<ul>
<li>User-friendly warnings when filters result in an empty data set</li>
<li>Consistent footer and header notes in the tables titles that match the Pilot 1 output</li>
</ul>
<p>The only outstanding issue that is still being worked on is the warning message that results from loading the <code>teal</code> package from GitHub because it is not yet on CRAN.</p>
<p>The Pilot 2 resubmission is now scheduled for 9AM PST on Wednesday July 19, 2023. Note that shortly after the meeting the date was confirmed with Beverly Chin and HyeSoo Cho.</p>
<p><strong>Action</strong> JBR to schedule a zoom meeting and invite:</p>
<ul>
<li>HyeSoo Cho</li>
<li>Beverly Chin</li>
<li>Ning Leng</li>
<li>Eric Nantz</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<p>Joel Laxamana provide the status update on Pilot 3.</p>
<ul>
<li>The Pilot 3 team is developing the testing process and updating the ADRG to follow the process used in Pilots 1 and 2.</li>
<li>Developing the testing process is taking longer than expected because they are attempting to develop a hybrid of the different process used in Pilot 1 and Pilot 2.</li>
<li>The group is now targeting the first or second week of August for the Pilot 3 submission.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Joel will confer with Eric and Nan at a separate meeting.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<p>Eric began the status update by thanking the team members from Appsilon who have set up a robust container environment for the Pilot.</p>
<ul>
<li>Saghir has been able to get the container and app running in his environment</li>
<li>We must work with the FDA to determine the best method of transferring the container</li>
<li>Team members from Posit are working with the the WebAssembly</li>
<li>The major technical requirement is that the FDA reviewers will be able to run the <a href="https://podman.io/">Podman</a> container environment</li>
<li>Right now, we believe that the WebAssembly, if it works as advertised, would be preferred by the FDA</li>
<li>It was noted that that FDA primarily works in a Windows environment</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>JBR to discuss FDA constraints and preferences with Paul Schuette.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM PST on Friday, August 4, 2023</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-07-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-06-02</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-06-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Andrew Borgman (Bristol Myers Squibb)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (JnJ)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Kui Shen (Bayer)</li>
<li>Loan Robinson (Bayer)</li>
<li>Miriam Fossate (Merck)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Nate Mockler (Biogen)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Shannon Lewis</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="minutes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minutes">Minutes</h2>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/O_pRQJl9E9Wq5mesygYFA4KTfVAudRq1Y8YIW3VwCrsr6LpV-9Lg4nfD3TuJs1a6.ewHmJNFkhrTRByzx?startTime=1685721888000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<p>JBR brought the meeting to order and Paul Schuette gave an account FDA analyst HyeSoo Cho’s findings so far with respect to the Pilot 2 submission. Identified problems include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Warning messages about packages being loaded from GitHub. (Packages should be loaded from CRAN or some other curated repository which archives packages.)</li>
<li>Footnotes and reference numbers that appeared in the previous Pilot 2 submission were missing from some tables.</li>
<li>Instead of remaining unchanged, some p-values were replaced with the text “non applicable” when filters were applied to the KM curve.</li>
<li>It is possible to create an empty data set with conflicting filters.</li>
</ul>
<p>Although all agreed that these were relatively minor problems, it was nevertheless agreed that we should ask Hye Soo to stop her review, while Eric Nantz fixes the problems. The end goal is to have Pilot 2 be as clean as possible to serve as a model for future work.</p>
<p>The new schedule is to arrange for a new Pilot 2 Submission by the end of June. We will arrange for a new submission date when Eric is ready.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<ul>
<li>There was no Pilot 3 update</li>
<li>The additional work on Pilot 2 will cause the Pilot 3 submission to be pushed back to the end of July.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<ul>
<li>Eric Nantz announced that the Pilot 4 kickoff meeting will happen next work</li>
<li>Engineers from Appsilon will join the Pilot 4 team. They are particularly interested in investigating the <a href="https://webassembly.org/">WebAssembly</a> technology and have experience with containers.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the Submissions WG will be at 9AM Pacific Time on Friday, July 7, 2023.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-06-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-05-05</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-05-05/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Andrew Borgman (Bristol Myers Squibb)</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Brandon Suchon</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Kui Shen (Bayer)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Nate Mockler (Biogen)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Sean Healey (Pfizer)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="add-minutes-here" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="add-minutes-here">Add Minutes Here</h2>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/OZyp5N4QZCsl-D-8BMBzjuSubI0BYbISZTa6703egO97UUroboDFZVt4hjRudEY.1qe8A653kLrj7tfz?startTime=1683302886000">video</a> is available.</p>
<p>Joseph Rickert brought the meeting to order.</p>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<ul>
<li>Hye Soo Cho of the FDA reported that her review of the Pilot 2 submission is going well and that she expects to be finished in June.</li>
<li>She is not sure how long it will take the FDA to produce a written response.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<p>Joel Laxamana reported on Pilot 3 work.</p>
<ul>
<li>The execution team isfocusing on documentation particularly in the ADRG.</li>
<li>The WG confirmed that Pilot 3 should follow the Pilot 2 approach and send the renv.lock file in the R package text.</li>
<li>There was a question about SDTM Versions. The WG confirmed that the Pilot 3 should use the same 1.4 STDM version as Pilots 1 and 2. See <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam/issues/104">Issue #104</a>.</li>
<li>QC Findings will go as Appendix to the ADRG.</li>
<li>The WG agreed that the second week in July would be a good target for Pilot 3 Submission.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<p>Eric Nantz provided an update on Pilot 4 work.</p>
<ul>
<li>Eric expects to have the first meeting of the execution team volunteers in the next few weeks.</li>
<li>Eric is taking a step back from committing to a container based approach in order to consider the possibility of using a self executing app in the browser using <a href="https://webassembly.org/">WebAssembly</a>.</li>
<li>George Stagg from Posit is providing some assistance.</li>
<li>The idea is that the R submission code would run in a browser on the local machine of an FDA analyst.</li>
<li>Paul Schuette indicated that this approach would likely be possible at the FDA.</li>
<li>Eric said that he would be happy to try and replicate the FDA web browser environment.</li>
<li>The group suggested that a Webinar for the R Adoption series and other venues would be valuable for promoting the project.</li>
<li>Paul speculated that this web browser technology might also be useful to FDA field inspectors.</li>
<li>Eric noted that a selection core of R packages is being identified to have them run run “out of the box”.</li>
<li>If you would like to be part of the Pilot 4 team please contact Eric Nantz.</li>
<li>Paul noted that recent events where outside entities can re-litigate FDA approvals decades after the approval could make it even more necessary to be able to run analysis software many years after the submission.</li>
<li>JBR surmised that there may be interest in WG to explore long term archiving.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="other-discussions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-discussions">Other discussions</h3>
<ul>
<li>Nan Xiao brought attention to a <a href="https://www.jpma.or.jp/information/evaluation/results/allotment/DS_202204_oss.html">document</a> describing the submission WG in Japan. It refers to a survey about open source that mentions the Pilot 1 Submissions.</li>
<li>We are exploring the possibility of arranging for the authors of this document to participation in an R Adoption Series webinar.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the Submissions WG will be on Friday, June 2, 2023 at 9AM Pacific Time.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-05-05/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-04-07</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-04-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Amanda Martin</li>
<li>Andrew Borgman (Bristol Myers Squibb)</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Kui Schen (Bayer)</li>
<li>Lei Zhao (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Nate Mockler (Biogen)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Sean Healey (Pfizer)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-2-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2-update">Pilot 2 Update</h2>
<p>Eric Nantz provided the following update:</p>
<ul>
<li>He has solved the filtering bug and has verified the app is working correctly with additional testing.</li>
<li>He is incorporating ADRG material into the intro guide</li>
<li>Paul suggested adding a list of steps and has offered to discuss details offline.</li>
<li>Ning will work with Bev to make sure we are good to go with the gateway</li>
<li>The Pilot 2 re submission is set for 9AM on Friday, April 21, 2023. Joe will schedule the meeting (Bev, Eric, Hye Soo, Paul, Ning)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3-progress-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-progress-update">Pilot 3 Progress Update</h2>
<p>Joel Laxamana provided the following update.</p>
<ul>
<li>All 5 ADaMs now generated and in review.</li>
<li>Per development steps, we have noted discrepancies or findings when comparing our Pilot 3 ADaMs with the original Pilot 1 ADaMs. You may see these noted in our Wiki here : https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam/wiki/QC-Findings .</li>
<li>Minor updates are being made to clean up code, updating our variable labels appropriately and updating the ADaM specifications (define) to meet CDISC guidance as we go through our routine P21 checks.</li>
<li>We are also currently developing our ADRG based off of the Pilot 3 specifications we are reading into P21. We plan to use the P21 ADRG as a base, then we will add in information similar to that of Pilot 1 for complete instructions prior to submission.</li>
<li>As we finalize both the define and the ADaMs, we are also developing a batch run code to run all of our ADaM and TLF scripts, with that we are looking into implementing dependency recognition using a package called {targets} (e.g.&nbsp;before ADAE is run, checks latest ADSL code has been run first).<br>
</li>
<li>Additionally, we are rerunning all TFL scripts from Pilot 1 and re-sourcing the Pilot 3 data.</li>
<li>Once the above is finalized, we will do a batch run, check against P21, then bring everything over into our eSubmission repo. We have made contact with Roche’s Regulatory function who will help support the preparation of our eSubmission in eCTD structure.</li>
</ul>
<section id="current-project-workflow-discussion-as-seen-in-pilot-1" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-project-workflow-discussion-as-seen-in-pilot-1">Current Project workflow discussion as seen in Pilot 1:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Upon reviewing Pilot1’s work and the R4CSR guidance they have followed, we see the current flow suggests the use of 2 repos : 1)Project repo &amp; 2)Submission repo</li>
<li>In the project repo, this includes the project analysis R scripts (ADaMs and TFLs) and R utility functions within the same package.</li>
<li>14.2.2 programs</li>
<li>Folder path: ectddemo/m5/datasets/ectddemo/analysis/adam/programs/.</li>
<li>r0pkgs.txt: contains all internally developed proprietary R packages. Other .txt files: each contains R code for a specific analysis.</li>
<li>They also suggest using .RMD files as the source analysis scripts, which are then converted to .R/.txt for submission.</li>
<li>Then all .txt are brought over to the Submission repo to deliver to Regulatory for eCTD structure and formal submission to the FDA portal.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>In Pilot 3 our project flow emulates more of the usual project work we would see in our companies.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>For instance, our source code will just use plain .R instead of .RMD as source analysis code. Especially for ADaMs, it make more sense to just start in .R scripts.</p></li>
<li><p>For the most part Pilot3 will follow the same submission process as Pilot1, but the minor difference will just be our project flow. I.E., Pilot 3 will separate the Utility functions from the Project analysis scripts into different repos. It makes more sense to treat the study specific utility functions as separate package, similar to how we call on other R packages from CRAN or other git repositories, where then the project analysis repo scripts will call on the aforementioned study specific utility functions package. This is still in line with the R4CSR guidance in section 14.3<br>
</p></li>
<li><p>Following this approach, makes it clear from a study perspective where the utility functions are being called from, where the project analysis scripts are stored and developed and where the submission will be. For illustration purposes we have this graphic (Thanks, Thomas Neitman!):</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-04-07/repos.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Proposed Pilot 3 Repo Setup</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, to our Health Agencies, the single source of truth will of course come from our ‘Submission’ repo, where they may not need all of the details of the study project flow steps. We just wanted to be able to discern that R packages should be kept in their own packages and project analysis work should not be stored as a package.</p>
</section>
<section id="post-meeting-notesactions-from-r-consortium-submissions-wg-07apr2023" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="post-meeting-notesactions-from-r-consortium-submissions-wg-07apr2023">POST Meeting notes/actions from R Consortium Submissions WG (07Apr2023) :</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Per Paul Schutter, Pilot 3 needs a link to the ‘FREE’ P21 version that the Pilot 3 team should be using. Paul to share link with Joel. We should also include SDTM in the P21 run, but just mention in the ADRG that we will not be updating or fixing the SDTMs due to any P21 issues to follow the same approach as Pilot 1. Though Pilot 3 is mainly focused on ADaMs, we do plan on fixing the P21 issues the best we can and noting discrepancies compared to the CDISCPILOT data.</li>
<li>Need new repo from submission_wg to store the utility functions into. Joe R, could you help us with this?</li>
<li>For the study project repo set-up, there are example template repos that can be followed. Pilot 3 team to look into this.</li>
<li>Targeting mid-June 2023 to wrap-up submission.</li>
<li>Link to all Pilot 3 members, for Eric to include in Submission WG webpage : https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot3-adam/main/</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<p>Eric Nantz gave a brief update:</p>
<ul>
<li>Eric is starting to build a team and already has some volunteers</li>
<li>The effort will focus on container technology</li>
<li>Paul Schuette will reach out within the FDA to find an FDA participant for this group</li>
<li>Paul noted that anything having to do with servers would necessarily involve the use of contractors and have to have a budget.</li>
<li>There may be a way to have the container run on a laptop and thus avoid the complications caused by servers. *Ning Leng asked Paul if there are any other groups within the FDA that might be interested in pilots. Paul replied that the guidance he has received from management is to hold off on this for the time being.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="asa-webinar" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="asa-webinar">ASA Webinar</h2>
<p>JBR Informed the WG that the ASA New Jersey Chapter has contacted him about doing a webinar on the Submissions WG. The email below outlines a list of options.</p>
<ul>
<li>The WG was enthusiastic about doing a robust webinar with multiple talks sometime after the Pilot 2 submission in June.</li>
<li>Paul said that he would like to participate and asked if other ASA members could attend. Paul noted that he has had requests to speak from pharma companies, but it is difficult for FDA speakers to speak to individual companies without committing to speak to all companies.</li>
<li>The WG would like to co-brand the event as an <em>R Adoption Series Event</em></li>
</ul>
<section id="march-26-2023-email-from-sciling-ruan" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="march-26-2023-email-from-sciling-ruan">March 26, 2023 email from Sciling Ruan</h4>
<p>Hi Joe,</p>
<p>It was very nice to speak to you last week and learned about what you do in the R-Submission working group. As discussed, we are very interested in collaborating with you to bring the topic of R-submission to our webinar. I also include our ASA NJ Chapter President Dirk Moore in the loop. Dirk is a faculty member in Rutgers University, and he will also help organize the webinar.</p>
<p>I understand that you will need to discuss this collaboration within your working group. I would like to give more information in case it might be helpful.</p>
<p>The webinar can have one presentation or multiple presentations with different perspectives. So I would be interested to know the tentative presentation titles and speakers.<br>
The webinar can be set in any date and month. We are very flexible. Normally, to accommodate both east coast and west coast audience, we often recommend the time slot of 11:00-12:00 or till 1:00 EDT on a Friday.<br>
We might invite another speaker from a pharma company on their experience with R-submission (if we could identify a good speaker). In that case, the webinar will be two hours with a panel discussion. Will this set up OK with you? Once I have some information to work with, we will follow up with a kickoff meeting including all potential speakers to work out the details. The webinar will use the WebEx platform in Rutgers University. It will be a free event to everyone.</p>
<p>I look forward to hearing from you. If you need more information from me, please let me know.</p>
<p>Best regards, Shiling Ruan</p>
</section>
<section id="additional-conferences" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-conferences">Additional Conferences</h3>
<p>In general, the WG is keen about promoting their work after the submission of Pilot 2 and the group discussed possible opportunities for talks alter this year including the R / Pharma conference and possibly and FDA event. The group will discuss this at the next meeting.</p>
<p>The next meeting of the WG will be at 9AM Pacific Time on Friday May 5, 2023.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-04-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-03-03</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-03-03/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Kui Schen (Bayer)</li>
<li>Lei Zhao (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Sean Healey (Pfizer)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://positpbc.zoom.us/rec/share/q2j9oskw1QXsUzjeI9NfdvBFYZcy6ml1aqCqGYRmtUC_NeH7RYUKePzyfj-e1OIS.y_DcC-vgNR4sVWjw">video</a> is available.</p>
<p>Due to a problem with zoom permissions, the meeting started 15 minutes late. Apologize to everyone who was inconvenienced.</p>
<p>(At 1:37 into the video) HyeSoo Cho begins sharing here screen and providing her comments on the recent Pilot 2 submission.</p>
<p>A bug in the submission code caused population subsetting in the Kaplan Meier Curve to propagate silently throughout the <code>shiny</code> app. During the course of the meeting Eric Nantz was able to identify the problem as a incorrectly set option and correct it.</p>
<p>JBR noted that turning off subgrouping for everything but the KM plot was a special requirement for the pilot submission and asked if under normal operation whether the FDA reviewers would like the <code>shiny</code> app to display this default behavior. (The alternative would be for app users to remember to turn on the same subgrouping for every plot or table in order to make comparisons.) HeySoo and Paul Schuette provided an explanation of the FDA’s need to be very careful of subgroup analysis.</p>
<p>Paul emphasized that it is very important to distinguish between “exploratory analysis” and analysis for “inferential analysis”. Subgrouping that causes p-values to change cross the line between the two types of analyses. The FDA is very concerned that the misuse of subgrouping could lead people to improperly argue for evidence of efficacy based on restricted subpopulations. When asked if he was advising that submissions should not contain interactive capabilities Paul replied “No”. He elaborated that nothing interactive should produce a p-value.</p>
<p>(10:48 into the video) Ning Leng asked if subpopulation analyses associated with predefined endpoints would be permissible as this would distinguish between inferential and exploratory analyses. Paul replied this is correct. He noted that prespecified subgroup analyses will often product confidence intervals but not p-values.</p>
<p>(At 19:56) Eric announced the resolution to the parameter problem and the group agreed that we have a path forward for the current Pilot 2 submission. Eric also suggested that the interactivity may be the biggest topic for the group to discuss. Paul asked to defer the discussion of this bigger issue and suggested that the working group look to the <a href="https://amstat.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2016.1154108#.ZAKTTuzML0q">ASA statement on p-values</a> for guidance.</p>
<p>(18:36) The FDA does not want to be seen as endorsing the practice of rescuing a “failed” clinical trial by torturing the data. He noted that even now there is a problem with JMP and other tools that that are interactive but do not produce an open and fully transparent analysis true.</p>
<p>Interactive tool must be open, transparent, reproducible, and consistent with good statistical practices. Paul suggested that an interactive tool that produces interactive tools on demand may not be consistent with the ASA statement on p-values.</p>
<p>In response to a question, Paul affirmed that the ASA statement in p-values is a good foundation for understanding FDA practices.</p>
<p>(22:57) Begins a discussion on <a href="https://github.com/rstudio/shinymeta"><code>shinymeta</code></a> and reproducibility. It as also noted that the <a href="https://insightsengineering.github.io/teal.code/main/articles/teal-code.html">teal</a> project is also addressing this reproducibility issue.</p>
<p>(27:43) HeySoo resumes her comments on the Pilot 2 submission by commenting on the warning and error messages generated by the submission code, and points out that referencing a repository other than CRAN is problematic. Paul noted that FDA IT security is insisting on strong security checks, but that a case can be made that CRAN provides sufficient checks. He said that his group at the FDA is floating the notion of “curated” packages.</p>
<p>HeySoo suggested that providing a README file that discusses all the potential error and warning messages and what needs to be done to run the app properly. Paul noted that some of this information should be included in the app to make it as stand alone as possible.</p>
<p>The working group agreed that the next step should be to produce an updated Pilot 2 submission package and resubmit it through the gateway. This will make it for the FDA to produce a written response. We will proceed with Pilot 2 take 2.</p>
<p>Eric will deploy will a new version on our internal host so that everyone can review it before the second submission.</p>
<p>When asked if the FDA security work Paul mentioned would lead to a guidance document, Paul replied that it may and noted that there is an internal FDA working group addressing the problem, and that currently Python appears to be a bigger security problem than R.</p>
<p>(44:26) Paul informed the group that the FDA is being approached by multiple groups, including PhUSE and Transcelerate, about using R and validation issues. The FDA would coordinate the activities of these groups to prevent duplication of effort and decide who is going to do what. He also suggested that we should broaden our base within the FDA and seek to get John Scott and CBER involved.</p>
<p><strong>Action</strong> JBR will invite someone from the R Validation Working Group to attend our next meeting and meet with Paul to identify a representative from PhUSE to invite.</p>
<p>The next meeting of the Submissions Working Group will be on Friday, April 7, 2023 at 9AM PST.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-03-03/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-02-03</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-02-03/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Juliane Manitz (EMD Serono)</li>
<li>Luke Schantz (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Stephanie Lussier (Moderna)</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang (Meta)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/play/_r36eqGi8QfcrTyUn9Gq9dGJ3PrcVSImESyURrrHORDRgH3eZMl339Ay2v-_WgcYnoNv7l_OGv7dB7A.ceeNzouCunCUAi3I?continueMode=true&amp;_x_zm_rtaid=Od0rcCEIQBqAiOnyBePFDQ.1675462941996.dacb4db0c1d380b6173ed3092354bc50&amp;_x_zm_rhtaid=571">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<p>Eric Nantz provided a summary of the Pilot 2 submission status:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>As previously reported, Paul confirmed that he was able to open submission and run the code.&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>Paul also reported some minor differences from what was expected, received some warning messages and found some differences when running in different environments.</p></li>
<li><p>Hye Soo sent an email saying that she expects to be able to complete her evaluation in time to present her finding at the March 3, 2023 meeting.</p></li>
<li><p>Eric offered to work with Paul and the Hye Soo to resolve a</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<p>Nan Xiao summarized some of the topics discussed at the recent Pilot 2 meeting and pointed to some of the issues on GitHub. In particular, he highlighted the discussion about whether Pilot 2 should wrap the submission in an R package as was done in Pilot 1 and Pilot 2.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Joel, a lead for the Pilot 3 group, joined the meeting and provided an update. (31:54 into the video)</p></li>
<li><p>The group is making progress with data sets and tracking differences from those used in Pilot 1</p></li>
<li><p>This month the team is focusing on finalizing data sets and generating output.</p></li>
<li><p>The group has had some discussion about packing the submission</p></li>
<li><p>The Submission WG members were in general agreement that Pilot 3 should conform to the standards set in Pilot 1 and Pilot 2 and use the package paradigm.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<p>Eric briefly described the mission of this Pilot to make use of container technology, and noted that one goal is to make the use of containers easier for non experts.</p>
</section>
<section id="meeting-invitation-issue" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meeting-invitation-issue">Meeting invitation Issue</h3>
<p>The group noticed that not everyone is getting the submissions to the Submissions WG meeting.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Luke will relaunch the Submissions WG meeting and make sure that the Pilot 3 folks are also invited to the general submissions WG meeting</p></li>
<li><p>JBR and Luke will work together to determine who should receive invitations.</p></li>
<li><p>JBR wants to make sure that although inactive members will be removed from the current invitation list, we will keep a record of their participation and maintain a list of current and past WG members somewhere on the website.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="new-submissions-wg-website" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-submissions-wg-website">New Submissions WG Website</h3>
<p>At 17:45 into the video Eric presents the new Quarto based website he has created for the WG. Eric has automated many of the task required to generate minutes and track members.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Joel will work with Eric to build out the Pilot 3 part of the site.</p></li>
<li><p>Eric will select a time to provide a tutorial on using the website for JBR and Luke and record the session to share with others.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="discussion-about-device-submissions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion-about-device-submissions">Discussion about Device Submissions</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>JBR mentioned that in a recent conversation asked if this group Robert Gentleman would be interested in R based device submissions.</p></li>
<li><p>Paul noted that there is already a group making device submissions.</p></li>
<li><p>See the <a href="https://www.niss.org/news/niss-merck-meet-discusses-open-source-software-pharma-april-21-2021">video</a> of the recent NISS-Merk meetup for some details. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tarek-haddad-07003a10/">Tarek Haddad</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tedlystig/">Ted Lystig</a> could provide more information.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.fda.gov/about-fda/center-devices-and-radiological-health/cdrh-offices">CDRH</a> does not have these same CDISC structure that <a href="https://www.fda.gov/about-fda/fda-organization/center-drug-evaluation-and-research-cder">CDER</a> and <a href="https://www.fda.gov/about-fda/fda-organization/center-biologics-evaluation-and-research-cber">CBER</a> have.</p></li>
<li><p>CDRH has different requirements and is more flexible than CDER and CBER. The restrictions imposed by the CDER gateway generally has to do with accommodating large data sets. In general, CDRH data sets are not so large.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Paul offered to contact John Scott, Director of the CBER Biostats group, to see if his group has any interest in submissions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="transcelerate" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="transcelerate">Transcelerate</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>Paul noted that there was a recent FDA meeting with <a href="https://www.transceleratebiopharmainc.com/">Transcelerate</a> in which Transcelerate proposed projects to which Paul responded that some of the proposed work is already being done by the Submission Working Group.</p></li>
<li><p>Paul also noted the RC work is going well.</p></li>
<li><p>JBR asked if we should reach out to Transcelerate and Pau suggested Keaven Anderson of Merck</p></li>
<li><p>Paul offered to make introductions to the R Consortium if they are willing.</p></li>
<li><p>JBR noted that the RC is very willing to welcome Transcelerate into its efforts.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The next meeting will be at 9:00 AM Pacific Time on Friday, March 3, 2023.</strong></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-02-03/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2023-01-13</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-01-13/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Andrew Borgman (Bristol Myers Squibb)</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Bob Engle (Biogen)</li>
<li>Doug Kelkhoff (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Kevin Kunzmann (Boehringer Ingelheim)</li>
<li>Luke Schantz (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Phil Bowsher (Posit)</li>
<li>Ryan Johnson (Posit)</li>
<li>Sean Healey (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Stephanie Lussier (Moderna)</li>
<li>Steven Hasendinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Tadeusz Lewandowski (Roche/Genentech)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/apmL_9HvbAo" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="pilot-2-update" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2-update">Pilot 2 Update</h3>
<ul>
<li>Paul Schuette confirms he was able to successfully run the Shiny application</li>
<li>They encountered a few messages that they ignored, as the app still ran successfully</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho followed the ADRG instructions and launched Shiny app, without major issues</li>
<li>She noticed minor issues around errors and warning messages. As part of her evaluation she tried launching the app in different machines to compare results. She saw some inconsistency between the environments, and they will report specific findings by next month (February)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3-update" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-update">Pilot 3 Update</h3>
<ul>
<li>Proposal was sent in early December for comments and feedback <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam/issues/37" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam/issues/37</a></li>
<li>Running into minor issues with using the same specifications and define settings as the original Pilot 1</li>
<li>They are not clear on the most up-to-date specifications to use for the AdAM creation, would like help from others</li>
<li>Thomas found a Phuse 2017 white paper on transport files for the next generation. This paper proposed new ways to convert the data before transfer</li>
<li>Additional ideas such as a proposal to use JSON format <a href="https://wiki.cdisc.org/display/ODM2/Dataset-JSON" class="uri">https://wiki.cdisc.org/display/ODM2/Dataset-JSON</a></li>
<li>FDA is aware of the proposal, but it is not clear how far the proposal has gone</li>
<li>Study Data Technical Conformance Guide details the latest specs and what is acceptable in the gateway <a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/162867/download" class="uri">https://www.fda.gov/media/162867/download</a></li>
<li>Sponsors can use SAS version 8 of XPT if they choose, most sponsors are using version 5 from their experience</li>
<li>Other pilots have explored alternative formats, but have not been satisfactory in their opinion</li>
<li>It is common to convert the XPT format to a more consumable format. For instance as sas7bdat in SAS or R objects inside R.</li>
<li>Pilot 3 will adhere to the current specifications</li>
<li>Ben recommended consulting with Sam Hume as a collaborate to push the effort along</li>
<li>The ectd gateway would need updating to accommodate json formats. That would require discussions with the E-data team in the FDA</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="r-validation-hub-intro-to-repositories-working-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="r-validation-hub-intro-to-repositories-working-group">R Validation Hub intro to Repositories working group</h3>
<ul>
<li>Doug Kelkhoff and Kevin Kunzmann led a an introduction to the mission and goals of the working group</li>
<li>Mission is to support a transparent cross-industry approach of maintaining a repo of R packages with evidence of their quality and assessment criteria</li>
<li>Repo structure may resemble pieces of CRAN, R Universe . Still in the early stages of finding what is needed before working on the technical solutions</li>
<li>Asks for regulatory input: Work with the team to understand how you want to observe quality. Paul mentioned that bigger issues that FDA are thinking about are from the IT perspective (making sure that packages don’t compromise infrastructure). Example of haven running into buffer overflow issues. Typically those concerns are raised by security team colleagues. They are not aware of any independent effort to gauge the quality of an R package. Typically they point people to the R Validation Hub. While it is not doing independent replication of algorithms, it is a reasonable attempt in the right direction. Typically all pieces of software give you the “as-is” message and no implied guarantee of quality</li>
<li>Asks for industry input: Contribute by direct support, or by intermittent feedback as they prepare deliverables</li>
<li>High level of planned deliverables: List of quality criteria, mockup of the communication portal, and an example of a package server modelling a real-world workflow</li>
<li>Visit the repository to get involved <a href="https://github.com/pharmaR/regulatory-r-repo-wg" class="uri">https://github.com/pharmaR/regulatory-r-repo-wg</a></li>
<li>Ben asked about ways to consolidation various validation efforts heard from other sponsors. What existing tools are being implemented in this space?</li>
<li>Doug shared an article from the ASA Biopharmaceutical Report regarding the risk assessment of R packages: <a href="https://www.pharmar.org/blog/2022/12/05/2022-12-05-asa-biopharmaceutical-report-fall-2022/" class="uri">https://www.pharmar.org/blog/2022/12/05/2022-12-05-asa-biopharmaceutical-report-fall-2022/</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2023-01-13/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2022-12-02</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-12-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Bob Engle (Biogen)</li>
<li>Brian Sucher (Unknown)</li>
<li>Christopher Kania (Biogen)</li>
<li>Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</li>
<li>Ellis Hughes (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Miriam Fossati (Merck)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Phil Bowsher (Posit)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Ryan Johnson (Posit)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Stephanie Lussier (Moderna)</li>
<li>Thomas Neitmann (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Xin Qiu (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang (Meta)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<ul>
<li>Ning Leng and Eric Nantz reported that Pilot 2 was submitted on 2022-11-18, upholding the working groups tradition of submitting right before Thanksgiving, and that confirmation was received from the the FDA.</li>
<li>Paul Schuette explained that since Pilot 2 was not a production submission it was necessary to make a manual request to receive it. Consequently, his group did not receive it until earlier this wee.</li>
<li>Heysoo Cho said that she will begin working on the submission next week.</li>
<li>Eric Nantz offered to be available to help if the FDA had any questions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h3>
<p>Joel Laxamana briefly reviewed the preparations his team is making for Pilot 3 and said that the proposal is ready for transmission to the FDA. Paul suggested that the proposal should be sent to everyone in the working group and not just the FDA. Joel agreed to put the proposal in the Submissions WG GitHub repository and send the link to everyone in the working group.</p>
<p>Joel noted that many of the Pilot 3 concepts were taken from the ADRG for Pilot 2 and mentioned that they are checking against the CDISC versions as they build the package.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h3>
<p>Eric said that he hopes to ramp up Pilot 4 work after the Pilot 2 submission. The simplest plan will be just to containerize the Pilot 2 submission. <a href="https://podman.io/">Podman</a> is the initial choice for a the container technology.</p>
<p>The group also expressed about aligning the Pilot 4 project with the Validation Hub to stand up a repo of validated packages. This would open up the possibility of hosting the container on the validation repo. The Validation Hub repo for this project is: https://github.com/pharmaR/regulatory-r-repo-wg</p>
</section>
<section id="other-business" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-business">Other Business</h3>
<p>JBR asked Ning and Joel for summary paragraphs for Pilot 2 and Pilot 3 for inclusion in end of the year reports on working group status. Ning is working on a blog post about Pilot 2 for inclusion in the R Consortium Blog.</p>
<p>There were no updates available about efforts to make pilot submissions to other regulatory agencies.</p>
<p>The following events were identified as possibilities for delivering presentations:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Appsilon Shiny conference: <a href="https://shinyconf.appsilon.com/">ShinyConf 2023</a> March 15-17 - Ning and Eric are drafting an abstract</li>
<li>R/Medicine June 8-9</li>
<li>R/Pharma</li>
<li>useR! 2023</li>
<li>Posit::conf</li>
<li>ASA BioPharma SWE Workshop in September</li>
</ul>
<section id="other-future-plans" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-future-plans">Other future plans:</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ning noted that she and Yilong have been thinking about a journal submission and have begun writing a draft.</li>
<li>The group also agreed that they would like to do another R - Adoption Webinar.</li>
<li>Finally, Eric noted that he would like to rework the Submissions repository site and build it on a Quarto framework.</li>
<li><strong>The next meeting of the Submissions WG will be at 10AM PST, Friday 13, 2023.</strong> This is a one week delay to move the meeting beyond the holiday season.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-12-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2022-11-04</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-11-04/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Bob Engle (Biogen)</li>
<li>Ellis Hughes (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Gregory Chen (MSD)</li>
<li>Heng Wang (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Honghong Zhou (Moderna)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Lei Zhao (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Stephanie Lussier (Moderna)</li>
<li>Tadeusz Lewandowski (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang (Meta)</li>
<li>Yiwen Luo (Merck)</li>
<li>Yutong Liu (Moderna)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LDVWXgDhzzo" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LDVWXgDhzzo">video</a> is available on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC_R5smHVXRYGhZYDJsnXTwg">R Consortium YouTube Channel</a></p>
<p>The meeting began with EN summarizing his understanding of the comments made by PS about his preliminary look at the Pilot 2 submission package.</p>
<p>The following is a summary of Paul’s comments which were made in a email exchange with the workgroup members on 10-27-22:</p>
<ul>
<li>Paul has management approval to proceed with Phase 2 of the pilot, with the proviso that the Demographic, Primary and Efficacy Tables are static.</li>
<li>There is a minor error in the app: the low dose and high dose column settings reversed.</li>
<li>The efficacy table is slightly misleading as it currently stands. Suggest that the text for the first row read “Study Drug (High Dose)” or similar.</li>
<li>Suggest an additional table: “Subjects Remaining in the Study” showing how dropouts proceed. (See Paul’s email of 10-27-22 for details) This might show how exploratory analysis might add value over the prespecified</li>
<li>The number of decimal places displayed in the demographic table isn’t always the same as in pilot 1.</li>
<li>Suggest that the model specification information be included with the efficacy table rather than left to the app information.<br>
</li>
<li>We would like the app to be able to serve as a model for future submissions.</li>
</ul>
<p>Eric stated that the updates appear to be relatively minor and would not be difficult to accomplish.</p>
<p>The submission team agreed to target 11-18-2022 as the target submission date.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> JBR to put a 9AM 11-18-2022 on the calendar for the submission.</p>
<p>JBR asked Paul to describe the boundary between a useful amount and too much interactivity in a shiny submissions app. Paul replied that it a way to think about it would be the difference between exploratory and inferential analysis. The problem with inferential analysis is the usual problem with p-values, subgroups and cherry picking. Inferential analysis is not the way to go. A Kaplan-Meier curve would be considered an exploratory safety analysis.</p>
<p>When asked if the guidance on interactivity was likely to stand for some time or change with familiarity Paul replied that it was his personal opinion that since it is consistent with the <a href="https://www.amstat.org/asa/files/pdfs/p-valuestatement.pdf">ASA Statement on p-values</a> it will probably stand.</p>
<p>Paul also remarked that interactivity facilitating pre-specified analyses would probably be fine.</p>
<p>The following links may be helpful with understanding potential problems with on subgroup analyses:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/19466315.2015.1077726">Alosh et al.&nbsp;(2015)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/sim.7167">Alosh et al.&nbsp;(2016)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Joel Laxamana gave an update on the Pilot 3 effort:</p>
<ul>
<li>The kickoff meeting for the team was held this past Wednesday</li>
<li>There are 13 people on the team</li>
<li>The goal of Pilot 3 is to duplicate Pilot 1 but also generate the ADaM data sets used for the TLGs in Pilot 1</li>
<li>The idea is to start with the <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/standards/foundational/sdtm">STDM</a> and show the traceability to <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/standards/foundational/adam">ADaM</a></li>
<li>Pilot 3 will use the <code>admiral</code> package along with <code>tidyverse</code> packages.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> Joel will add this explanatory material to the Pilot 3 GitHub repo.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> Joel will send a list of Pilot 3 team members to be added to the invitation list for this meeting.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> The Pilot 3 team will submit a written proposal to the FDA describing the process of unpacking the submission and setting up for analysis. The target date is to have this proposal ready for the 12-02-2022 Submissions WG meeting.</p>
<p>Lei Zhao asked if it would be a problem submitting data in SAS in doing the analysis in R. In general there is no problem, however the FDA suggests using a limited number of tools and using standard tools to do any translations between formats. The FDA prefers using scripted languages as opposed to using a GUI.</p>
<p>Ning will be presented at the R/Pharma conference on Wednesday, November 9, 2022 at 11AM Eastern Time. The next meeting of the regular meeting of the group will be at 9AM Pacific Time on Friday, December 2, 2022.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-11-04/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2022-10-07</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-10-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ellis Hughes (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Honghong Zhou (Moderna)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Lei Zhao (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Miriam Fossati (Merck)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Phil Bowsher (Posit)</li>
<li>Qin Li</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Ryan Johnson (Posit)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Sean Healey (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Tadeusz Lewandowski (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Thomas Neitmann (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang (Meta)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://rstudio.zoom.us/rec/share/OfSxaPPUsLuFJtZeUjzsZ6kZoAtCn7GTAj-N1j4zU9gUXOI8NqU5SUXf7rbeG2eu.q4s5o6ZiCBJHId8h?startTime=1665158653000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-2-submission" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2-submission">Pilot 2 Submission</h3>
<p>Ning began her update on the Pilot 2 Submission by thanking everyone who helped with the testing.</p>
<p>Status: The submission package is ready. However, the submissions team must address some last minute comments from the FDA. One comment is a request to mask p-values that are automatically reported. The apparent concern is that by default p-values will automatically be updated and reported when users filter the data by subgroups. Because we only have a small test data set this will likely lead to widely varying p-values which could be misinterpreted by general reviewers who are not statisticians. The FDA may request additional outputs to me masked. These comments appear to address the long term use of interactive applications in submissions and are not related to the technical aspects of making the submission.</p>
<p>Consequently, the meeting scheduled for next Tuesday which was intended for submitting Pilot 2 will now be devoted to addressing FDA comments. The team will reschedule the submission as soon as possible after addressing the comments. We do not anticipate a long delay. There are no technical difficulties with masking additional default outputs.</p>
<p>In the meantime more testing would be helpful and appreciated. Follow the instructions in the Appendix for Pilot 2: https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot2/issues/46 Put issues here: https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot2/issues/</p>
<p>JBR noted that there is now significant material in the GitHub repository for the working group which is indicative of the scope and scale of cooperation of the project. This is itself a success story of some interest.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3---adam" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3---adam">Pilot 3 - ADaM</h3>
<p>(<strong>13:51min</strong> into the video) Thomas Neitmann presented a proposal by Joel Laxamana and himself to extend Pilot 1 to include ADaM datasets programmed in R. The purpose of the proposal is to:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Demonstrate the viability of using R for ADaM dataset creation in the context of an FDA submission</li>
<li>Provide the industry with an end-to-end example of an R-based FDA filing</li>
</ol>
<p>Thomas’ presentation may be found here: https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-wg/tree/main/Documents</p>
<p>Yilong suggested taking ODM XML as the source to make it more representative of an end-to-end process. This started a discussion about the value of beginning end-to-end examples from various different starting file formats.</p>
<p>The present team team includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Thomas Neitmann - Roche (Co-Lead)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana - Roche (Co-Lead)</li>
<li>Lei Zhao - Roche</li>
<li>Nicole Jones - Merck</li>
</ul>
<p>The team is looking for additional help. Please have a look at the presentation and contact one of the Co-Leads if you would like to get involved.</p>
<p>The working group agreed to change the name of the project from Pilot 1-ADaM Extension to Pilot 3-ADaM to emphasize that the project will include a significant amount of new work.</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong> JBR will make Paul Schuette aware of this new project and ask for his feedback.</p>
</section>
<section id="da-japan-talk" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="da-japan-talk">DA Japan Talk</h2>
<p>(<strong>31:30</strong> min into video) Tadeusz presented a Shiny application that he developed for a presentation he is going to make at the <a href="https://www.diaglobal.org/en/conference-listing/meetings/2022/10/19th-dia-japan-annual-meeting-2022">DIA Japan conference</a> on October 9, 2022. The intention of the presentation is to gauge the interest of the Japanese authorities. The session in which Tadeusz will present is called <a href="https://www.diaglobal.org/en/conference-listing/meetings/2022/10/19th-dia-japan-annual-meeting-2022/agenda/09/ls09?ref=LS09">LS09 Innovative and Dynamic Statistical Analytics for Regulatory Submissions</a></p>
</section>
<section id="subgroups" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="subgroups">Subgroups</h2>
<p>The working group discussed writing writing some material for the GitHub repository explaining the purpose of the various subgroups, listing the members, and explaining how newcomers can get involved.</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong> Joe and Eric will meet after the Pilot 2 submission to discuss documenting the subgroups.</p>
</section>
<section id="containers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="containers">Containers</h2>
<p>The working group agreed that the planned project to submit a containerized version of the Pilot 2 submission will require a significant amount of new work and pose several challenges. It should therefore be new, independent pilot submission, perhaps Pilot 4-Containers.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-10-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2022-09-02</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-09-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Bob Engle (Biogen)</li>
<li>CG Wang</li>
<li>Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</li>
<li>Ellis Hughes (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Gabriel Becker (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Helena Sviglin (FDA)</li>
<li>Henry Wang (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Lei Zhao (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Rupam Bhattacharyya (University of Michigan)</li>
<li>Ryan Johnson (Posit)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Sean Healey (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Thomas Neitmann (Roche/Genentech)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://rstudio.zoom.us/rec/share/DMHSikDsLtJ67qT8a6ivbiKZOnTuSkW_1ynV2PiTTslmtNR2dZNxtKsm77UzXyKn.raWC6wXreCYmkC1g?startTime=1662134754000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="ema" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ema">EMA</h3>
<p>JBR started the meeting by asking if thee was any news about the effort to submit to the European Health Authorities. Ning Leng replied that the European Medicines Agency announced a new <a href="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/other/information-about-raw-data-proof-concept-pilot-industry_en.pdf">pilot project</a> where they will run a number of pilot studies over the next couple of years in which they will accept data and code. Ning said that her team discussed this with Chris Price of whose who said that the EMA would want to review real data. This appears to preclude the R Consortium from participating from this effort. However, the group agreed we would be happy to help a sponsor company submit an R pilot.</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong> if there is sponsor company interested in submitting R code as part of an EMA pilot project, the RC Submissions WG would be happy to help an participate in a shared learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-2" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-2">Pilot 2</h3>
<p>Ning Leng and Eric Nantz gave an update on the Pilot 2 project Eric is testing the Pilot 2 submission on Windows virtual machines using two version of R v4.1.2 and 4.2.0.</p>
<p>Paul Schuette confirmed that the FDA team would prefer to keep the Pilot 2 deployment on a local machine and Eric said that the documentation is being written from that point of view.</p>
<p>Eric needs the RC credit card to proceed with the shinyapps.io deployment.</p>
<p><strong>Action Items</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Eric would like help testing the Pilot 2 Windows deployment. WG members please help with the testing process.</p></li>
<li><p>JBR will speak with Elisa Trevino to generate the credit card for the shinyapps.io setup.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>** Ning will email the WG when the submission documents are ready for review. WG members please help with this review.</p>
<p><strong>Target Date for Pilot 2</strong> Ning and Eric agreed that Monday, September 26, 2022 is the target date for the Pilot 2 submission.</p>
</section>
<section id="japanese-and-chinese-authorities" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="japanese-and-chinese-authorities">Japanese and Chinese Authorities</h3>
<p>Ning believes that the companies are interested in proceeding with pilot R submissions but the authorities are reticent because they do not have the resources to review pilots.</p>
<p>JBR commented that it appears that our pilot approach is not appropriate for China and Japan and ask the group to think about alternatives for approaching these authorities.</p>
<p><strong>Pilot 3</strong> Eric said that he recently spoke <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/martinwimpress/?originalSubdomain=uk">Martin Wimpress</a> and authority in this area who strongly recommends <a href="https://podman.io/">podman</a> which is considered an open source, binary equivalent to docker.</p>
<p>The group agreed that we should build a podman team that comprises representatives from at least two or three different companies as well as a representative from the FDA. Paul Schuette volunteered that he would ask his FDA management to assign someone to the team. T</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong> WG members please look within your companies to recruit people with the podman expertise for the Pilot 3 team. Paul noted that another FDA center has approval for podman and the it would take him a couple of months to obtain similar approval for his center. the WG would like to launch the container team at the October meeting.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-1---adam" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-1---adam">Pilot 1 - adam</h3>
<p>Ning introduced Thomas Neitmann and Joel Laxamana who are creating a proposal to construct a submission that would use the R to generate ADaM data from the cdisc data used in Pilots 1 and 2. The project would make use of the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=admiral"><code>admiral</code></a> R package.</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong> JBR will ask the RC to create two repositories under the R Consortium organization on GitHub: <strong>submissions-pilot1-adam-extension</strong> and <strong>submissions-pilot1-adam-extension-to-fda</strong> . Ideally the former would be a fork of the submissions-pilot1 repo and the latter a fork of the submissions-pilot1-to-fda repo.</p>
</section>
<section id="describe-the-sturcture-of-subgroups" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="describe-the-sturcture-of-subgroups">Describe the Sturcture of Subgroups</h3>
<p>There was a request to describe the Submission WG subgroups sufficiently for newcomers to find their way around. The main website for the subgroups is https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg</p>
<p>JBR asked the subgroup leaders to list all of the individuals who participated in the various subgroups, even those who may now be inactive.</p>
<p>The group agreed that it would be appropriate to keep a record of everyone who helped with the working group in order to recognize their contributions. We</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong> Subgroup leaders should list participants, and write a couple of sentences about how newcomers can get involved.</p>
<p>The next meeting of the submissions working group will be at 9AM Pacific Time on Friday, October 7, 2022.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-09-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2022-08-05</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-08-05/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Gabriel Becker (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Henry Wang (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sean Healey (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Xin Qiu (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang (Meta)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://rstudio.zoom.us/rec/share/LUb3xNKOTGzzC3kzAmElw-ye0vvdcvalqDV9oRpEUaIHjaHzUdb9gBORXxhYjRPi.7jbqiKpboFOHCHpH">video</a> with passcode: wW@9+Lbx</p>
<p>NL asked if the R Consortium could establish an RStudio connect server to host the Pilot 2 Shiny submission App which is currently deployed on a Genentech server (https://genentech.shinyapps.io/FDA-app/).</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong>: JR will contact RStudio to see what it would take to set up the server.</p>
<p>NL and EN reported that the Pilot 2 team is in the final stages of preparation. The team recently set up Pilot 2 on the <a href="https://thinkr-open.github.io/golem/"><code>golem</code></a> framework. <code>teal</code> has been fully incorporated, and the team is in the finals stages of completing the documentation preparing the submission. NL estimates that a submission in mid August is possible.</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong>: JR will connect with James Black to determine how Roche wants to announce the open sourcing of <code>teal</code>.</p>
<p>JR asked for updates from the efforts to make pilot submissions to the authorities in Japan and China. Based on conversations with her Roche colleagues, NL reported that there have be no new developments. The Japanese agency doubts that they have the resources to evaluate a pilot submission. The Chinese authority still appears to be interested in an industry collaboration. Roche China is attempting to form a working group, Ning offered to put anyone interested in touch with here Chinese colleague leading this effort.</p>
<p>JR asked: under the assumption that Pilot 2 goes really well, does the WG have any concrete suggestions for advancing the use of Shiny in submissions. EN noted that just getting Shiny in the process is a big step.</p>
<p>There was some discussion about the target audience for the Pilot 2 submission, and how the Shiny app might appeal to a larger FDA audience than the statisticians who would review a submission.</p>
<p>There was a questions about whether FDA reviewers would want to reproduce the Shiny app interactivity. PS noted that FDA reviewers are not Shiny app developers and it is unlikely that the FDA would want to go down that path. GB asked for clarity on the term “independent reproducibility”. PS noted that running the sponsors code in the same environment used by the sponsor is not considered to be independent verification.</p>
<p>NL asked about specific use cases that may be of interest to the FDA. PS noted that standing up a Shiny app in a real product submission workflow would be more complicated than one might expect because it would have to be integrated into an FDA contractor’s workflow. Using the current infrastructure, it is best to think of a Shiny app being run on an individual’s computer.</p>
<p>The discussion turned to the use of containers for submissions. JR asked PS whether about the FDA landscape for containers. PS replied that currently <a href="https://podman.io/">podman</a> has been approved by NCTR, and that if we would like to use that he would have to get approval for <a href="https://www.fda.gov/about-fda/center-drug-evaluation-and-research-cder/cder-offices-and-divisions">CDAR</a> use. Docker is not viable in the short term because of the subscription model, which would require coordination among multiple offices.</p>
<p>ER noted that in addition to podman and Docker he had identified singularity as a possible candidate container technology, but that this product is not as accessible to developers. In his organization, singularity requires an IT administrator to setup. PS noted that if this working group would identify a preferred container technology, he could begin promoting our choice within the FDA.</p>
<p>YZ asked if we should think about writing up the Pilot 1 and Pilot 2 experience for a journal publication, perhaps a two page letter. The group liked the idea and suggested R journal, ASA Journals, Significance, Chance, DIA Journals, JSS, JAMA and a clinical trials journal were suggested as possibilities.</p>
<p>NL asked about the possibility of presenting to FDA statisticians. PS said that he would have to consult with FDA management.</p>
<p>PS suggested something like the recent R Adoption Series Webinar which drew 600 people from industry would be viable. He would invite members of the internal FDA Statistics Association to attend. He suggested a discussion / capstone effort: “Working through the R Consortium industry and the FDA have collaborated with industry in an appropriate way and gone through a step by step process that has involved the FDA at each step.</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong> JR and NL to arrange this webinar.</p>
<p>Next the grouped discussed whether it would be worthwhile to do an additional pilot that would include data generation. The idea would be to start with <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/standards/foundational/sdtm">CDISC SDTM</a> data and derive the data for analysis such as change from baseline etc. PS said that this would be interesting, but that most reviewers start with the analysis data steps. More motivated reviewers will trace key variables to show that they can be independently reproduced. No decision was reached on this matter.</p>
<p>PS suggested that the WG consider participating in the <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/events/webinar/tfl-designer-virtual-workshop">CDISC TFL Designer Virtual Workshop</a> which will be held on 13 September 2022, 11am - 2pm Eastern Time. <a href="https://cdisc.zoom.us/webinar/register/WN__4u86BaeQImcA-U5tJ1pyQ">Register Here</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Action Item</strong> The group will try to find someone from CDISC who may involved and also search for someone from the working group who might want to attend. JR will write to James Black to see if he has any knowledge of the event.</p>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM Pacific Time on Friday, September 2, 2022.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2022-08-05/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
