<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>R Submissions Working Group</title>
<link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.34</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-09-05</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-09-05/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Conor Moloney</li>
<li>Doug Kelkhoff (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Jared Woolfolk (Cytel)</li>
<li>Keaven Anderson (Merck)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Orla Doyle</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Phil Bowsher (Posit)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Stephen Clieply</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="welcoming-new-attendees" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="welcoming-new-attendees">Welcoming New Attendees!</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stephen Clieply</li>
<li>Orla Doyle</li>
<li>Conor Moloney</li>
<li>Jared Woolfolk</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="rpharma-summit-and-gatherings" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rpharma-summit-and-gatherings">R/Pharma Summit and Gatherings</h2>
<ul>
<li>For anyone attending the 2025 R/Pharma Summit and/or <code>posit::conf(2025)</code>, Phil Bowsher shared that there are plans for social gatherings possibly for the evenings of September 14 and September 15. Be sure to check the R/Pharma <a href="https://github.com/rinpharma/rinpharma-summit-2025">summit repository</a> for updates!</li>
<li>The R/Pharma summit board is open to new members and input on the rountable session topics. Visit the summit <a href="https://github.com/rinpharma/rinpharma-summit-2025/discussions">discussion board</a> for details.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-updates">Pilot 4 Updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>Earlier in August, Eric led two leanring sessions on the fundamentals of containers built with Docker with FDA reviewers and interested members of the working group.</li>
<li>The recordings for these session can be found on the revampled <a href="https://rpodcast.quarto.pub/submissions-wg-pilot-4/tech_session.html#pilot-4-container-information">Pilot 4 web site</a></li>
<li>The next learning session will cover the fundamentals of WebAssembly technology and how the Shiny application included in the Pilot is converted to WebAssembly. Eric will coordinate with the FDA reviewers on timing of this next learning session.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5-updates">Pilot 5 Updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ben shared the current state of Pilot 5 efforts.</li>
<li>Current status: Debugging issues with using Pinnacle 21 Community edition
<ul>
<li>At this time, the community edition incoporates the datasetJSON 1.0 standard</li>
<li>However, pilot 5 is using the more recent datasetJSON 1.1 standard</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Ben asked if others in the group have experience with updating the community edition to the latest standard
<ul>
<li>Paul mentioned that the community edition is used at the FDA, and recommended reaching out to the Pinnacle 21 team.</li>
<li>Is this a showstopper for the submission?</li>
<li>If the XPT files are converted within Pinnacle 21 to convert to JSON, then those converted files seem to pass the conversion test.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The R package <a href="https://atorus-research.github.io/datasetjson/"><code>{datasetJSON}</code></a> uses the 1.1 standard</li>
<li>Additional effort: Create the integrated report of the TLFs that use the datasetJSON files</li>
<li>Additional polishing is ongoing with the ADRG. Ben and Eric will finish up the remaining minor issues in the next week.</li>
<li>Ben, Eric, Eli Miller, and Ning Leng recently led an exciting webinar on how Pilot 5 utilizes the power of <code>{renv}</code>, CI/CD with GitHub Actions, and novel uses of LLMs in partnership with the R Consortium. You can view the recording of the webinar on the R Consortium <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8U_9sQdr2WE">YouTube Channel</a>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="esub-portal" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="esub-portal">eSUB Portal</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ning informed the group that certain text files such as README and DESCRIPTION files do not require a suffix of <code>.txt</code> in order to pass the submission gateway portal.</li>
<li>This is a very important development, as certain files required by R packages such as <code>DESCRIPTION</code> cannot have their name modified or they will not be considered a valid R package in the R session.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="new-pilot-idea-ars" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-pilot-idea-ars">New Pilot Idea: ARS</h2>
<ul>
<li>Orla and Lovemore shared a set of slides about analysis results standards (ARS)</li>
<li>Novo Nordisk and Novartis are actively developing tools using the CDISC ARS (Analysis Results Standards) to help structure this format as well as the required metadata</li>
<li>Exploring the possibilities of a submission (such as what files would be part of a submission, and how it would be submitted)</li>
<li>How would this effort compare with existing tools such as cards package? The cards package will give youa piece of that result, but this effort helps to augment these pieces with the necessary metadata and ensure that the results could be produced by the metadata</li>
<li>With the data being machine readable, we have a lot of possibilities for how they are consumed by other frameworks such as AI based tools</li>
<li>The cards package does not cover all analyses, so these tools would add additional functionality</li>
<li>Up to this point, there has not been a discussion with regulatory on the adoption of the CDISC ARS specifications. But a new pilot could help provide valuable feedback</li>
<li>Ning mentioned that these efforts are in an early stage</li>
<li>Paul is not aware of a process underway with FDA on the ARS effort. However the team that would have handled that responsibility was impacted by recent events</li>
<li>At this moment, Paul’s team is in the division of statstical programming issues, where this pilot idea requires buy-in from other groups at the FDA that might require a more formal process from other divisions</li>
<li>Orlo expressed concern on the tools being developed in the ARS effort might get too far ahead and we find out later that the tools may not be acceptable for submission</li>
<li>October WG meeting could be an opportunity to continue the discussion and potentially invite lead of the CDISC group looking at this space</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="submissions-wg-and-r-validation-hub-collaboration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="submissions-wg-and-r-validation-hub-collaboration">Submissions WG and R Validation Hub Collaboration</h2>
<ul>
<li>Doug Kelkhoff led the discussion on the potential of a new collaboration with the Submissions Working Group on using new package repositories in a test submission.</li>
<li>Visit the R Validation Hub <a href="https://pharmar.org/">site</a> for additonal background on the group and contributions.</li>
<li>Current effort is to kick off a repository of pre-assessed packages</li>
<li>Potential to bring a pilot to this group for using the new repository</li>
<li>Since there isn’t a pre-defined new set of analysis, this pilot could integrate nicely with a previous pilot that performed an analysis, but with the packages from this repository</li>
<li>Doug reviewed key sections of the group’s <a href="https://pharmar.org/white-paper/">white paper</a>:
<ul>
<li>Components of a Risk Assessment Framework</li>
<li>Some are facts, others are how to intrepret these facts</li>
<li>They are trying to de-couple these two pieces</li>
<li>Create a database of these “facts” and let user decide if it is appropriate for their work</li>
</ul></li>
<li>New packages as part of a re-imagining of the risk assessment framework:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pharmaR/val.criterion"><code>{val.criterion}</code></a>: Decision-making tools for <code>{val.meter}</code> package metrics</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pharmaR/val.repo"><code>{val.repo}</code></a>: A curated repository of R packages that is structured similarly to CRAN but with additional metadata: It hosts validation reports on its associated website, published via GitHub Pages.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pharmaR/riskscore"><code>{riskscore}</code></a>: A data package for cataloging <code>riskmetric</code> results across public repositories.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The new framworks allow the user to link their R session up to a repository, alongside a metrics repository, and supply their own filters</li>
<li>What are the possibilities of using this in a future pilot?
<ul>
<li>Paul mentioned that there isn’t a formal software validation team at FDA</li>
<li>Separate teams handle the e-submission process</li>
<li>Validation of the software is up to the end-user groups such as the office of biostatistics, they can help determine the tools appropriate for their workflows</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Doug mentioned that typically the only feedback a sponsor receives on this type of effort is through an inspection</li>
<li>Short term idea would be to target the “end-user” group like we’ve been doing up to this point with previous pilots</li>
<li>Paul asked for a crafted proposal (1-2 pages) that he could share with colleagues in different divisions such as the office of compliance, hence their division can facilite while technical details would be outside of their responsibilities</li>
<li>Doug is supportive of creating that initial proposal, they can edit an existing writeup to target a compliance division as the target audience.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-09-05/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-08-01</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-08-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Gabriel Krotkov</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jayant</li>
<li>Jim Rothstein</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Phanikumar Tata (Syneos Health)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Sasi Palanisamy</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-5-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5-update">Pilot 5 Update</h2>
<ul>
<li>Team is working on the ADRG for Pilot 5</li>
<li>Aiming for a transfer to FDA reviewers near the end of August</li>
<li>Goal is to have ADRG wrapped up by middle of August</li>
<li>The team is going to adopt an approach from J&amp;J for setting paths to relevant data directories and R files at the start of execution</li>
<li>Meeting minutes https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-wg/discussions/150</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="ectd-file-type-feedback" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ectd-file-type-feedback">ECTD File type feedback</h2>
<ul>
<li>Link to issue https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-wg/discussions/150</li>
<li>Unique to R, many programmers write R scripts with the <code>.R</code> extension</li>
<li>eCTD transfer portal automatically renames any files with a capital letter are converted to lower-case</li>
<li>Package structures tend to have many file types, it may not be sustainable to try and list all of the different possible files</li>
<li>FDA does hope to have the zip archive’s file types be listed in the acceptable file list</li>
<li>In light of resources available, it could be advantageous to prune the list to the essential types and moving the “nice to have” file types could be a subsequent update</li>
<li>Certain file types such as <code>DESCRIPTION</code>, <code>NAMESPACE</code> <code>LICENCE</code> are actually plain-text files, but they need to be named as they are in order for an R package to be compiled correctly as a ZIP installer</li>
<li>Next steps: FDA will have internal discussion to propose the essential file types</li>
<li>Next step: Ensure that the proposed file types also include recommended use cases that could inform the updated ECTD guidance document</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-08-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-07-11</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-07-11/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Andre Couturier (Sanofi)</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Hong Zheng</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Nicholas Raymond</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Stephanie Lussier (Moderna)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-4-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-update">Pilot 4 Update</h2>
<ul>
<li>Hye Soo shared their group’s comprehensive initial feedback</li>
<li>Pilot 4 WebAssembly version: No major issues identified and the team was able to run the application.</li>
<li>Minor issues identified
<ul>
<li>In certain file paths that contained underscores <code>_</code>, something in the transfer process automatically converted the underscore characters to hypens <code>-</code>. The root cause is unknown at this time. As a result, portions of the file names referenced in the ADRG instructions had to be manually updated to ensure the application was able to run.</li>
<li>Hye Soo began investating a custom <code>index.xml</code> file that is produced at some point during the transfer, which is referenced in the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/159380/download">eCTD Backbone Files Specifications for Modules 2-5-3.2.2</a></li>
<li>Ning offered to discuss the issue with her colleagues with expertise in the transfer process to learn more about this issue.</li>
<li>Joel mentioned that during the Pilot 3 preparations, file names with underscore had to be converted to hyphen</li>
<li>Additional guidance on file conventions can be found in the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/85816/download">Specifications for File Format Types Using eCTD Specifications document</a>.</li>
<li>HyeSoo noted that certain elements of the WebAssembly application appeared differently than the Pilot 2 application. Eric noted that certain packages used for the data filtering involving Teal modules were not supported out of the box in the WebR package repositories at the time the application was created. At that time, Appsilon developers assisting with the Pilot 4 project re-implemented the filtering modules using native Shiny functions. Had the Pilot 4 WebAssembly project been launched in the present, these issues would not have been present as the Teal packages are now supported in WebR.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Pilot 4 Container version: Unfortunately major issues were identified that prevented successful execution of the application:
<ul>
<li>On the computers used by the reviewers, running Docker Desktop was not stable, and often would lead to unexplained crashes. They had to consult with their IT group for an attempt to solve these issues, one of the solutions was to update the version of the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL) on their machines. While that helped somewhat, they still experienced stability issues.</li>
<li>Multiple failures occurred during the process of building the Docker container image that prevented the image from being built successfully. Examples of the issues include packages not installing correctly (such as <code>{MASS}</code>), package repositories not able to be accessed (for instance the version of certain Teal packages that were used at the time of the Pilot 2 application development).</li>
<li>Eric shared that in his extensive testing involving Windows virtual machines, none of these issues were present and he was able to build and execute the application successfully. He acknowledged that even these virtual machines may not be fully representative of the various technical configurations added to the reviewers’ workstations due to IT policies and other administration settings.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>In light of these difficulties, Hye Soo noted that they would like to learn more about the processes and workflows used to create the Pilot 4 container submission bundle, as well as a general tutorial on the fundamentals in container technology. Unlike previous pilots focused solely on R installations, trying to debug issues preventing the Docker process from running as well as the Docker container images being built successfully is a difficult situation without additional knowledge on this technology.</li>
<li>Eric offered to set up a dedicated session with FDA reviewers and others from the working group to explore the fundamentals of the container process and the workflows used to develop Pilot 4. Additional details will be shared in the Slack channel.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5-update">Pilot 5 Update</h2>
<ul>
<li>On track for getting a first submission ready by the end of July</li>
<li>View the group’s latest meeting minutes on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson/discussions/3#discussioncomment-13732444">this link</a>.</li>
<li>In progress: Pull requests to add the hex stickers to the repositories!</li>
<li>They are trying to get ahead of issues that could be identified by the reviewers, such as creating the KM plots using updated packages that might alter appearances</li>
<li>Novel tooling being used in the QC pipelines. You can view Eli Miller’s QC GitHub action workflow at <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson/blob/main/.github/workflows/qc.yaml">this link</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming-events" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming-events">Upcoming Events</h2>
<ul>
<li>R adoption series webinar <strong>Open Source Software Adoption in Japan’s Pharma Industry: Key Findings from the 2024 JPMA R Usage Survey</strong>. Registration available at <a href="https://r-consortium.org/webinars/open-source-adoption-in-japans-pharma-industry.html">this link</a>. The webinar will be offered on July 23rd 5 PM PDT (July 24th 9 AM JST).</li>
<li>Another webinar schedule for August 28 focusing on Collaboration tools used in submission pilots (such as GitHub actions). Registration details forthcoming.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="proposal-cdx-and-open-source-in-submissions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="proposal-cdx-and-open-source-in-submissions">Proposal: CDx and open source in submissions</h2>
<ul>
<li>Hong Zheng shared an overview of their proposal for collaboration</li>
<li>With the rise of Clinical Diagnostics (CDx) co-development in targeted therapy approvals, there is an urgent need for the use of novel technology and open-source solutions to meet this challenge</li>
<li>They are proposing an effort to develop open-source tools based in R to modernize and streamline CDx submissions, aligning with regulatory (in particular the CDRH division at FDA to start)</li>
<li>The submissions WG is certainly eager to help share the learnings from our previous pilots and to be a resource for this new effort</li>
<li>An important next step is for Hong’s group to share their prototype package mentioned in their proposal</li>
<li>Also it will be important to identify a representative to contact in CDRH</li>
<li>Ning recommends to draft a proposal for a first pilot in this collaboration, ensuring the scope is clearly defined before engaging with CDRH colleagues.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="other-topics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-topics">Other Topics</h2>
<ul>
<li>Andre asked if ARDs will become part of future submissions?</li>
<li>Ning mentioned it is still early stage for the CDISC standard for ARD, but it will be worthwhile to investigate in a future pilot.</li>
<li>Andre mentioned they are creating internal tooling for the creation of ARDs using key inputs such as metadata.</li>
<li>The working group has discussed a few potential ideas for future pilots, and it’s becoming more important to capture these centrally. Eric will set up a GitHub discussion board with topics to capture these future pilot ideas.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-07-11/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-06-06</title>
  <dc:creator>Ning Leng</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-06-06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jared Woolfolk</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Keaven Anderson (Merck)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
<li>Terry Christiani</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<ul>
<li>Hye Soo provided an update on high level feedback of current pilot 4 submission</li>
<li>some discrepancy were found between the ADRG and the actual github folder structure, etc</li>
<li>outdated links were noticed in ADRG (e.g.&nbsp;https://cran.r-project.org/bin/windows/base/old/4.4.1/, moved from base/ to base/old/)</li>
<li>Hye Soo will work with Eric offline on the re-submission</li>
<li>Some issues Hye Soo encountered may be due to windows system versioning. If needed, we will engage more WG members to test the submission bundle using different windows versions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5">Pilot 5</h2>
<ul>
<li>Part 1 is near completion (reproduce pilot 3 contents but in json format)</li>
<li>Pilot 5 team will submit part 1 to FDA in late July. Will confirm the submission date in the July WG meeting.</li>
<li>The Pilot 5 team will initiate a discussion on the scope of pilot 5 part 2. In part 2, we will cover more complicated TLFs, and more ADaM data sets to make the submission closer to a real submission.</li>
<li>Eli implemented two <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson/pull/57">QC bots</a> for pilot 5 using github actions. One uses diffdf to check consistencies between pilot3 data and pilot 5 data; the second bot uses llm to check consistencies between pilot 3 graphs and pilot 5 graphs.</li>
<li>Ning used LLM to generate three tables of the ADRG <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-adrg-generation-pipeline/pull/12">PR</a>. The LLM generated, human reviewed tables will be included in pilot 5 ADRG</li>
<li>When generating new codes for pilot 5 part 2, the team may also consider using code assistants to write the first line code. (Roche is exploring building customized bots for admiral and NEST) ## Pilot 6</li>
<li>Keaven suggested exploring submission of html in pilot 6. The proposed scope is having an interactive report to assist review - especially for large tables such as AE tables, be able to drill down to specific terms and display listing of patients involved</li>
<li>Hye Soo and Paul commented that they are happy to explore the review of html as a supplementary material to the primary pdf file</li>
<li>will also explore submitting html version of ADRG</li>
<li>The pilot 5 team will align their part 2 scope to pilot 6 proposal, to make sure we maximize the reusability of the codes</li>
<li>Keaven will reach out to Merck individuals to seek interest of participation</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5-lessons-learned-webinar" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5-lessons-learned-webinar">Pilot 5 lessons learned webinar</h2>
<ul>
<li>We will host a R consortium webinar with the pilot 5 team. The focus will be on 1) how to use git efficiently among a relatively large team of collaborators, 2) the usage of github actions to build automated QC bots</li>
<li>Terry, Ning and Ben will organize the event</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="hex-stickers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hex-stickers">Hex stickers</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ben will finalize the design of the Hex stickers</li>
<li>Terry will help printing out the stickers and send to key WG members to distribute at conferences</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="sce-blog-2" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sce-blog-2">SCE blog #2</h2>
<ul>
<li>Jared asked whether there are any discussions on producing a whitepaper on container management (example topic: for a long running trial, what are the suggestions on when to upverison the container)</li>
<li>As we are at a very early stage of exploring of the usage of container in regulatory submission, we will start with a few interviews with big pharma and produce a blog post (similar to <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/the-crucial-role-of-release-control-in-r-for-healthcare-organizations/">this one</a>)</li>
<li>Jared agreed to lead this effort</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-06-06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-05-02</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz &amp; Theresa Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-05-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Athenkosi Nikonyeni</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Camilla Calmasini</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jared Woolfolk</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Keaven Anderson (Merck)</li>
<li>LG</li>
<li>Mekhala Acharya (Takeda)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Phanikumar Tata (Syneos Health)</li>
<li>Phil Bowsher (Posit)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Sadchla Mascary</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Stephen Knapp</li>
<li>Yilong Zhang (Meta)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<ul>
<li>Eric to set up a informal review meeting with FDA colleagues in Mid May (EDIT: The revised transfer will take place on June 13th, 2025)</li>
<li>Full speed ahead to use <code>{pkglite}</code> for assembling the web assembly and container submission bundles.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5">Pilot 5</h2>
<ul>
<li>Part 1 is moving well (conversion from xpt is complete)</li>
<li>Team will wait until pilot 4 review is complete before transferring pilot 5</li>
<li>Paul: Not sure where the evaluation of <code>datasetjson</code> currently stands within FDA. The team that was sponsoring it has been affected by recent events. They think the gateway will accept the format, but needs verification.</li>
<li>Previous transfers in the CDISC effort last year may or may not have been through the ectd gateway</li>
<li>ESUB team is still having discussion on testing the json format</li>
<li>Heather Crandle from a previous R Pharma conference is part of that team (2021)</li>
<li>In current <a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/85816/download">eCTD instructions</a>, JSON is allowed for the PK category<br>
</li>
<li>Ben will follow up with team involved in the CDISC pilot to see how they transferred the JSON files.</li>
<li>The team has embedded a datasetJSON viewer with shiny and webassebly in the pilot 5 website available at <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot5-website/viewer.html" class="uri">https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot5-website/viewer.html</a></li>
<li>Ning had started investing using LLMs to generate portions of the ADRG. There may be an update at the next WG meeting.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adrg-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adrg-updates">ADRG updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>The group’s approach is to help communicate the version of different packages and how to best display that information in the ADRG template.</li>
<li>Feedback has been received from FDA reviewers. The group is looking into ways to update templates such that multiple software languages can be supported</li>
<li>Keeping in close sync with Christine at Pfizer on ensuring the existing standards are being met.</li>
<li>Also have plans to contact reps from Pinnacle21 on how they populate the ADRG, while ensuring minimal overlap occurs.</li>
<li>Goal of the group is to reduce manual effort of populating the various tables in the ADRG such as package versions, number of programs, functions used in those programs, which is all a manual effort at the moment</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="other-topics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-topics">Other Topics</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yilong would like to know if there is interest in a Python-based pilot for submitting tables and listings produced in Python.</li>
<li>Thus far not as much interest in the office of Biostatistics according to FDA reviewers</li>
<li>CDRH handles things differently than CDER. CDRH does not require CDISC standards to be followed. A greater range of issues can occur in those cases.</li>
<li>Meta has utilized standards inspired by CDISC in their initial work</li>
<li>FDA is open to a more focused discussion, but they will need to pull in internal experts that have more expertise</li>
<li>Eric asked about the FDA having any preference on the method of rounding as there are rare cases where the default rounding method in R can be different than SAS default method</li>
<li>FDA does not have a “preferred method” to share at this time, and there may not be a single one answer that’s correct in this area</li>
<li>Pilot 1 had a small issue with rounding dealing with the approximation method for confidence intervals</li>
<li>We are looking for help on the website! Please get in touch with the working group and browse the <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-wg/issues">GitHub issue list</a> if you would like to contribute.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-05-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-04-04</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-04-04/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Andre Couturier (Sanofi)</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Camille Calmasini (Natera)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jim Rothstein (Freelance)</li>
<li>Keaven Anderson (Merck)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Nicholas Masel (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Phil Bowsher (Posit)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Tilo (unknown)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-4-web-assembly-and-docker-container-shiny-app" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-web-assembly-and-docker-container-shiny-app">Pilot 4 (Web-assembly and Docker Container Shiny app)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Eric has investigated the possibility of utilizing <code>{pkglite}</code> to assemble the submission files necessary for both the container and web-assembly versions of Pilot 4.
<ul>
<li>Container version: No issues, as the necessary Dockerfile can easily be renamed to <code>Dockerfile.txt</code> with the command to build the image updated accordingly. The existing Pilot 2 R files can be assembled alongside the aforementioned Dockerfile.</li>
<li>Web-assembly: As long as the pre-compiled version of the application is not included in the transfer, the modified application files and helper R scripts used to compile the application would still be using the permitted file types (R scripts, text files).</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The FDA reviewers would like a re-transfer of the web-assembly application using the new structure. The reviewers are in agreement to perform separate transfers for each of the Pilot 4 types, as trying to assemble each in to a single transfer package could introduce more complications as they require much different steps for running their respective applications.</li>
<li>Paul mentioned that any discussions on the future use of Zip archive files in ECTD transfers is being put on hold due to circumstances happening at the agency outside of their control.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5-dataset-json-format" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5-dataset-json-format">Pilot 5 (Dataset-JSON format)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ben shared that terrific process is being made:
<ul>
<li>The use of XPT files has been removed in favor of native <code>.rds</code> files for data storage.</li>
<li>Additional code cleanup is on track.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Next steps are to merge the candidate Dataset-JSON files into the main repostory.</li>
<li>Based on discussin in the March working group meeting, Ning and Nabil created a prototype workflow that leverages the <code>{ellmer}</code> pacage to populate portions of the ADRG using LLMs.</li>
<li>Thanks to Sam, we have a new page on the <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot5-website/viewer.html">Pilot 5</a> web site that embeds the DatasetJSON Viewer Shiny application.</li>
<li>Paul shared that the aforementioned “circumstances” have impacted the FDA’s internal resourcing on the Dataset-JSON effort. How this impacts the future of a Pilot 5 transfer is to be determined. As of now, there is still an embargo on written communications.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="phuse-metadata-adrg-working-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="phuse-metadata-adrg-working-group">Phuse Metadata / ADRG Working Group</h2>
<ul>
<li>Lovemore shared that preparation is underway for a interactive session at the Phuse CSS conference in Europe.</li>
<li>Team is working to build functions to gen metadata for the different sections of the ADRG, to be eventually folded into a package.</li>
<li>Christine from Pfizer shared the current template for the ADRG which will be distrbuted to the other team members. The group will determine how it aligns with comments previously provided by the FDA reviewers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="other-topics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-topics">Other Topics</h2>
<ul>
<li>The working group welcomes a new member: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/camilla-calmasini/">Camilla Calmasini</a>!</li>
<li>Ben reminded the group of an opportunity to add a <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-wg/issues/106">timeline</a> to the Submissions Working Group site, as a way to present visitors a quick visual of the many accomplishments coming from these pilots. A great example can be found on the <a href="https://insightsengineering.github.io/nest/">NEST</a> website. Another approach could be to leverage the <a href="https://daattali.com/shiny/timevis-demo/"><code>{timevis}</code></a> HTML widget authored by Dean Attali, as well as clever use of Observable to create an <a href="https://observablehq.com/@observablehq/build-your-own-gantt-chart">interactive Gantt chart</a>.</li>
<li>Lovemore shared that a new Phuse Working group called <a href="https://advance.hub.phuse.global/wiki/spaces/WEL/pages/90472489/QC+Workflow+Optimisation"><strong>QC Workflow Optimisation</strong></a> has launched to investigate the use of double-programming in the QC process of validating clinical programming. There could be opportunities for them to share an update with our group as they make progress, and to determine how future pilots may benefit. Ben mentioned this was a topic discussed in the recent PHUSE Connect, especially with how AI could help in this process.</li>
<li>Keaven asked the group how reproducibility is being addressed currently for Shiny applications?
<ul>
<li>The Teal framework leverages a [custom-build solution called <code>qenv</code>]*https://insightsengineering.github.io/teal.code/latest-tag/articles/teal-code.html() as documented on the <code>{teal.code}</code> package website</li>
<li>Phil reminded the group that the Shiny team created a package years ago called <a href="https://rstudio.github.io/shinymeta/"><code>{shinymeta}</code></a> to help application authors capture logic based on user interactions and create a reprodcuible R script to replicate those interactions.</li>
<li>Matthew Kumar &amp; Srinivas Verragoni from Bayer presented their use of <code>{shinymeta}</code> in a presentation titled <a href="https://phuse.s3.eu-central-1.amazonaws.com/Archive/2023/Connect/US/Florida/PRE_OS10.pdf">Reproducibility of Interactive Analyses</a> at the 2023 Phuse US Connect conference.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Bonus trivia: Why was the SAS JMP software called JMP? JMP was named as “John’s Mackintosh Program” as it was an early attempt within the company to make SAS compatible with the Apple Macintosh operating systems (h/t Paul).</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-04-04/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-03-07</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-03-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Katie Harding (Freenome)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Nabil Baugher (Baseline AI)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Nicholas Masel (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-4-file-structures" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-file-structures">Pilot 4: File Structures</h2>
<ul>
<li>Discussions internally are taking place at FDA on whether the Zip file can include the file types that may not be on the approved software list</li>
<li>In light of the evolving discussions, Paul recommends to explore the use of <code>{pkglite}</code> for bunlding the applicaiton files in a similar fashion as Submissions Pilot 2 (traditional shiny application)</li>
<li>Eric will examine both the web assembly and Docker container versions of Pilot 4 and provide FDA reviewers a list of the essenstial file types necessary to review each submission bundle</li>
<li>Nan Xiao recommends we examine his recent releaes of <a href="https://nanx.me/blog/post/pkglite-python/">pkglite for Python</a> in case that could help streamline the process, especially for the web-assembly version</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5-datasetjson" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5-datasetjson">Pilot 5: DatasetJSON</h2>
<ul>
<li>The pilot 5 team is aiming to have dataset programming completed by the end of March, and TLF programming completed by end of April.</li>
<li>Questions remain on whether the JSON format can be included as a submission format, Paul mentioned that they are waiting to confirm with the E-sub group internally</li>
<li>The R-Consortium Blog recently featured a <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/">fantastic post</a> announcing the launch of Pilot 5:</li>
<li>Minutes from the Pilot 5 working group meetings are available on the Pilot 5 datasetJSON GitHub repository: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson/discussions/3" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson/discussions/3</a></li>
<li>One potential benefit for education and awareness: Embed an example Shiny application inside the Pilot 5 Quarto website for users to explore contents of dataset JSON files.
<ul>
<li>After Robert shared a list of apps created in a recent DatasetJSON Hackathon, the team saw an apportunity with the <a href="https://github.com/sbarcelo777/Dataset-JSON-hackathon">Dataset-JSON Viewer</a> Shiny application</li>
<li>Sam Parmer quickly created a novel way to compile the application as a web-assembly Shiny app and dynamically deploy the app on Posit’s shinylive-R hosting platform to embed insde the Pilot 5 Quarto website as an iframe! You can view the page at <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot5-website/viewer.html" class="uri">https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot5-website/viewer.html</a></li>
<li>In parallel, Eric also experimented with compiling the same Shiny application into web-assembly, and has a prototype automatically deployed on GitHub Pages via GitHub Actions: <a href="https://rpodcast.github.io/Dataset-JSON-hackathon/" class="uri">https://rpodcast.github.io/Dataset-JSON-hackathon/</a></li>
<li>Eric will reach out to the developers of the Dataset-JSON viewer to see if they are receptive to Eric sending a pull request to have the application hosted from their GitHub repository (thus their GitHub Pages account). In addition, Eric will ask the maintainers if they would support having a slightly streamlined version of the application that pre-loads JSON data files created for this pilot.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Eric and other team members are currently updating GitHub actions for repository maintenance and automation</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="phuse-metadata-adrg-working-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="phuse-metadata-adrg-working-group">Phuse Metadata / ADRG Working Group</h2>
<ul>
<li>Joel Laxana shared the latest updates: They group is trying to hash out the information to be added in the ADRG for future open source submissions</li>
<li>During recent discussions, the team is going forward with creating a separate supplement document to go along with the traditional ADRG submission document in the case of an R-based submission</li>
<li>The group is reviewing feedback provided by FDA reviewers from the past couple of pilots submitted</li>
<li>The open source metadata working group will continue to leverage metadata from a particular project to populate sections of the document, using R functions that can help fill in manual steps</li>
<li>The group ponders if generative AI help to populate these templates?</li>
<li>While AI is not in the scope of the Phuse project, the team is open for exploration</li>
<li>Indeed there could be an opportunity to spin off a separate pilot on exploring generative AI in a clinical submission documentation preparation such as the ADRG.</li>
<li>A new channel will be created in the R Consortium Submissions Working Group Slack channel. For details on obtaining access to group, please visit the <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/join.html">How to Join</a> page.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="other-topics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-topics">Other Topics</h2>
<ul>
<li>Members of the wroking group (Ben, Sam, and Eric) will join Appsilon for the April 29th edition of <a href="https://events.ringcentral.com/events/shiny-gathering-fda-pilots-key-insights-lessons-learned-and-what-s-next-for-2025-820c22c5-9f84-4bb1-a9ba-9341ecaf791d">Shiny Gatherings</a> discussing the insights, lessons learned, and what’s next for 2025.</li>
<li>The group assured colleagues from FDA that there would not be any direct quotes shared from FDA colleagues inside of this webinar, and any issues from the regulatory side would be discussed in general terms.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-03-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-02-07</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz &amp; Theresa Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-02-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Katie Harding (Freenome)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Phanikumar Tata (Syneos Health)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Terry Christiani (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Vedha Viyash (Appsilon)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="adrg-metadata-group-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adrg-metadata-group-updates">ADRG metadata group updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>Lovemore and Sam shared the group’s recent updates progress. They recently invited Christine Rossin (from the Phuse ADRG working group) to their meetings for discussion on the proposed template.</li>
<li>Christine’s recommendations include moving the instructions for executing the R code and setting up the execution environment to a supporting document and not part of the ADRG itself, ensuring the ADRG remains software-agnostic, and separate guidelines be developed for specific software.</li>
<li>The metadata group will be taking the lead on authoring guidelines for the R exection and environment language</li>
<li>The group will also establish dialogs with other sub-teams addressing additional sections of ADRG such as such as estimands team to ensure everyone is on the same page for updating the ADRG sections</li>
<li>Next steps include authoring R scripts to help automate population of certain sections in the ADRG template.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4-container-submission-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-container-submission-updates">Pilot 4 Container Submission updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>Eric shared recent progress on assembling a proposed submission structure for the container portion of Pilot 4.</li>
<li>Substantial updates have been made to the development repository available at <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot4-container" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot4-container</a> as well as the proposed submission structure at <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot4-container-to-fda" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot4-container-to-fda</a>.</li>
<li>Eric will share the proposed structure with our FDA colleagues to ensure this is aligned with the eCTD guidelines.</li>
<li>Robert inquired about the specific version of the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL) used in the testing environment. Eric believes it is WSL2 but that will be confirmed and the appropriate sections of the ADRG will be updated accordingly.</li>
<li>Vedha shared that running the command <code>wsl --version</code> in the testing environment should output the key metadata on the WSL installation.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5-dataset-json-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5-dataset-json-updates">Pilot 5 DataSet-JSON updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>Sam and Ben shared the recent progress from the Pilot 5 working group</li>
<li>The team has created GitHub repositories for key portions of the pilot:
<ul>
<li>Development repository: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson</a></li>
<li>R package repository: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-utilities" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-utilities</a></li>
<li>Website: https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot5-website/</li>
<li>Submission package structure: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson-to-fda" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson-to-fda</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>The data sets and R code used in Pilot 3 will be ported over to the Pilot 5 repositories</li>
<li>The team is very interested in utilizing GitHub actions to perform quality checks of the data set</li>
<li><code>{datasetjson}</code> was recently updated to version 1.1 and the new update is available on CRAN. You can view the changelog at <a href="https://atorus-research.github.io/datasetjson/news/index.html" class="uri">https://atorus-research.github.io/datasetjson/news/index.html</a>.</li>
<li>As development begins for the quality checks and other testing, they will use the Pilot 3 code as a starting point.</li>
<li>Robert shared that CDISC will hold a general meeting on February 18, 2025. Members of the working group are encouraged to attend. Additional details and registration are available at the pharma-oversight Slack channel in the February 14, 2025 post.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-02-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2025-01-10</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz &amp; Theresa Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-01-10/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>CG Wang</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Katie Harding (Freenome)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Nikolay Nikolaev</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Phanikumar Tata (Syneos Health)</li>
<li>Phil Bowsher (Posit)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Terry Christiani (R Consortium)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="adrg-working-group-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adrg-working-group-updates">ADRG Working Group Updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>Lovemore provided an update on recent ADRG working group discussions, with minutes available at <a href="https://github.com/phuse-org/OSDocuMeta/pull/7/files" class="uri">https://github.com/phuse-org/OSDocuMeta/pull/7/files</a>.</li>
<li>Part of the recent discussions involved sharing the FDA’s proposed draft of ADRG content with Christine Rossin at Pfizer (a member of the PHUSE ADRG working group). She had many comments pertaining to keeping the ADRG template language-agnostic. The team will set up a</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-5-dataset-json-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5-dataset-json-updates">Pilot 5 (Dataset-JSON) Updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ben shared a two-stage approach to the pilot that mimics how Pilot 4 was split to two components</li>
<li>The pilot 5 team will hold weekly 30-minute calls on Fridays (10 AM EST) for discussions and updates.</li>
<li>At a high level the pilot will have two key stages of development:
<ul>
<li>Convert the data sets created in Pilot 3 to JSON.</li>
<li>Adding additional JSON data sets and possibly new TLGs for additional testing and to pinpoint edge cases.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Pilot 5 now has the following GitHub repositories created:
<ul>
<li>Development repository: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson</a></li>
<li>Submission (eCTD-struture) repository: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson-to-fda" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson-to-fda</a></li>
<li>R package repository: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-utilities" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-utilities</a></li>
<li>Pilot web site repository: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-website" class="uri">https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-website</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-6-realistic-submission-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-6-realistic-submission-data">Pilot 6 (Realistic Submission Data)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ateendees expressed excitement about the ways this new pilot’s data package could help many aspects of future submissions involving open-source software, ranging from the ability to handle larger data sets, to having custom versions of the data tailored to benchmarking statistical methodologies.</li>
<li>Paul reminded the group that while they have access to a vast set of data from submissions, they are not allowed to share sponsor data externally.</li>
<li>Ben had a suggestion that part of the pilot 6 deliverables include a mock study protocol and statistical analysis plan.</li>
<li>Eric will begin to create GitHub repositories for the pilot and set up working group meetings.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="additional-items" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-items">Additional items</h2>
<ul>
<li>The working group expressed interest in sharing publicly the new Pilot 5 and 6 objectives and goals in a future R Consortium Blog Post.</li>
<li>Nan Xiao has created a Python version of <code>{pkglite}</code> which is now part of the Pharmaverse! Details on the package can be found on GitHub at &lt;https://github.com/pharmaverse/py-pkglite?</li>
<li>The group discussed the possibilities of Python being part of future submission using multiple languages? Time will tell, but there could be a future Pilot that addresses the possibilitiy.</li>
<li>Paul confirmed that Python is acceptable in submissions per the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/85816/download">eCTD Specifications</a> document.</li>
<li>Terry informed the group about important efforts for open-source software repositories involving R to comply with the pending <a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/cyber-resilience-act">Cyber Resiliance Act</a> (CRA).</li>
<li>The R Consortium along with representatives from the R Foundation, Bioconductor, ROpenSci, and the new Multiverse project are in close collaboration to ensure their repositories meet the requirements of the act.</li>
<li>As of this writing, open-source software repositories must comply with the CRA mandates by December 11, 2027.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="joining-the-submissions-working-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="joining-the-submissions-working-group">Joining the Submissions Working Group</h2>
<p>A friendly reminder that you can find complete details on joining the Submissions Working Group at <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/join.html" class="uri">https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/join.html</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2025-01-10/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-12-06</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz &amp; Theresa Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-12-06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Amanda Martin (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert</li>
<li>Mike Stackhouse (Atorus)</li>
<li>Nicholas Masel (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Sam Hume (CDISC)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Terry Christiani (R Consortium)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="adrg-formats" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adrg-formats">ADRG Formats</h2>
<ul>
<li>HyeSoo shared additional feedback from FDA on the file formats used for sending the Analysis Data Reviewers Guide (ADRG) in clinical submissions:
<ul>
<li>For an FDA submission, a final ADRG document should be submitted for review. It is not recommended for reviewers to take additional steps such as rendering the ADRG using Quarto or another technical publishing system/package.</li>
<li>The PDF format is required for submitting an ADRG. However there is a possibility of conducting a pilot test with submitting the ADRG in alternative formats such as the source Quarto file <code>.qmd</code> as well as the HTML output format <code>.html</code>.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The rational for submitting an ADRG in HTML format was discussed. Eric and Joel shared that having the HTML format brings the possibility of interactive displays (such as tables) which could be beneficial, especially for a submission including a large amount of programs and TLG outputs.</li>
<li>The group agreed that sending the ADRG source file in <code>.qmd</code> format would not be as beneficial in the current stage, as the rendered document itself is the main focus.</li>
<li>Future pilots such as Pilot 5 could be the first project to test submitting the ADRG in HTML format</li>
<li>While Pilot 4 (WebAssembly Shiny app) formally submitted the ADRG in PDF format, Eric created a separate version of the ADRG in HTML format as a technical preview, which can be viewed at <a href="https://rpodcast.quarto.pub/pilot4-webassembly-adrg/">this link</a>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="ectd-and-zip-archives" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ectd-and-zip-archives">eCTD and Zip Archives</h2>
<ul>
<li>HyeSoo shared clarifications on the current eCTD specifications for including a ZIP archive file in a submission package. The accepted location is M5.3, with the permissible uses of grouping large sets of aECG XML files.</li>
<li>The method of including both the data sets and programs in the ZIP archive (utilized by the Pilot 4 WebAssembly submission) is not permissible.</li>
<li>Eric will set up a targeted discussion with Paul and HyeSoo in January 2025 on how to best utilized the ZIP format in the future Pilot 4 Docker Container submission.</li>
<li>Questions were raised on the possible inclusion of additional archive formats such as compressed Tar archives <code>.tar.gz</code> in the eCTD specifications. Currently that format is not supported, but it could be explored for discussion with FDA next year.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="dataset-json-overview" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dataset-json-overview">Dataset-JSON Overview</h2>
<ul>
<li>Sam Hume from CDISC joined the meeting to share CDISC’s efforts in creating JSON datasets for clinical submissions, and feedback from previous pilots with FDA. You can view slides from Sam’s previous presentation on Dataset-JSON from the 2024 CDISC &amp; TMF Europe Interchange conference at <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/sites/default/files/2024-04/2024-EU-Interchange-Session-6B-SamHume-final.pdf">this link</a>, as well as the slides from a Public Review webinar held by CDISC at <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/sites/default/files/pdf/Dataset-JSON-v1-1-Public-Review.pdf">this link</a>.</li>
<li>Many of the standards in data exchanges are now using the JSON format as default.</li>
<li>There is increasing interest in additional structures besides the traditional rectangular/tabular approach, such as in the Electronic Study Protocol Template M11 module.</li>
<li>CDISC ran a pilot within CDER at FDA to verify the Dataset-JSON format could be successfull transferred and viewed by reviewers. The testing was deemed successful.</li>
<li>A mix of tools were utilized in the pilot. One of the over-arching goals is to ensure that the Dataset-JSON format is agonostic to the tools/languages used to ingest the format. For example, multiple languages like SAS, R, and Python should be able to import and analyze the data in this format.</li>
<li>Recently the Dataset-JSON version 1.1 was released, addressing feedback generated from the earlier pilot. You can view the updated user guide for v1.1 at <a href="https://wiki.cdisc.org/plugins/servlet/mobile?contentId=230658980#content/view/230658980">this link</a>.</li>
<li>Mike Stackhouse shared that the <a href="https://atorus-research.github.io/datasetjson/">`{datasetjson}</a> package, tasked with reading and writing CDISC Dataset JSON files, is in active development to accomodate v1.1 of the Dataset-JSON format.</li>
<li>Nick and Mike would welcome collaboration from others on the package updates.</li>
<li>Another important fix ongoing for the package is switching to a more performant JSON processing backend, as detailed in <a href="https://github.com/atorus-research/datasetjson/issues/32">issue 32</a> of the package’s GitHub repository.</li>
<li>In light of learning about the successful pilot, questions were asked on whether our submissions group should still initiate a new Pilot that leverages JSON format instead of XPT. Sam and others in the call concurred that the pilot would still be worthwhile to conduct, as it could be the first test of the new Dataset-JSON v1.1 specification in a realistic setting.</li>
<li>Ben shared that this could be a great opportunity for others in the working group to take the lead on this new Pilot, now being called Pilot 5. Ben will take on the task of creating a new channel in Slack dedicated to Pilot 5 within the R Consortium Slack Channel.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="admin-housekeeping" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="admin-housekeeping">Admin &amp; Housekeeping</h2>
<ul>
<li>The group agreed to keep the current cadence of having the Submissions WG meetings on the first Friday of every month, with adjustments as needed.</li>
<li>A few members on the call were not clear on how to get invitations properly on their calendar. Theresa shared the ways anyone can add the working group meetings on their calendar. However the group agreed that having a dedicated page on the Working Group site for how to join the group and the various communication platforms would be a beneficial.</li>
<li>Eric will create a new page on the site to hold this information. In fact that page is now live! Visit the <a href="join.qmd">How to Join</a> page for complete details.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-12-06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-11-01</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz &amp; Theresa Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-11-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Katie Harding (Freemore)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Nicholas Masel (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Theresa Christiani (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="pilot-4-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-updates">Pilot 4 Updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>HyeSoo shared concerns regarding the appropriateness of zip file formats for program delivery under FDA specifications. Suggestions to explore new architectures or formats for future submissions were raised, particularly for web-based applications.</li>
<li>Testing for the Docker container component of Pilot 4 is ongoing, thus far no issues but Eric will share more updates in the next meeting.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="working-group-coordination" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="working-group-coordination">Working Group Coordination</h2>
<ul>
<li>Theresa Christiani introduced an inter-organization coordination committee to streamline overlapping efforts across working groups (R Consortium, PhUSE, Pharmaverse). This committee will promote efficient use of resources and avoid redundant work. Robert Devine volunteered to present at the next coordination meeting.</li>
<li>Robert will present at the R Consortium’s inter-organization coordination committee to share the group’s current projects and align efforts across R Consortium, PhUSE, and Pharmaverse.</li>
<li>Those interested in attending that coordinating meeting can contact Theresa for getting on the invitation to those meetings</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="analysis-data-reviewers-guide-adrg-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-data-reviewers-guide-adrg-updates">Analysis Data Reviewer’s Guide (ADRG) Updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>The PhUSE working group on open-source metadata documentation is working to update the ADRG template to better support open-source submissions, with feedback from FDA and industry representatives.</li>
<li>Lovemore gave a recap of a presentation about the ADRG workstream at the PHUSE FDA quarterly meeting</li>
<li>The team discussed the potential use of Quarto (QMD) and HTML formats for more accessible, navigable submissions, as well as potential supplementary documents for open-source submissions. Paul confirmed that R Markdown (<code>.rmd</code>) format has already been approved as a file type.</li>
<li>Joel and Lovemore will set up a future meeting to gather additional industry feedback as a first step to developing a new prototype of the ADRG using enhanced metadata and the Quarto format.</li>
<li>While Quarto is an approved software package at the FDA, and Quarto file format (<code>.qmd</code>) is part of the approved file types within the <strong>Modeling and Simulation</strong> section of the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/media/85816/download">eCTD Format Specifications</a> document.</li>
<li>Paul and HyeSoo will touch base with Helena Spiglin (part of the FDA committee currently assessing the <code>.json</code> formats as an alternative to SAS Transport <code>.xpt</code>) for confirming the Quarto and HTML formats can be added as supported formats for ADRG submissions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="data-set-json-format-and-alternative-data-formats" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-set-json-format-and-alternative-data-formats">Data Set JSON Format and Alternative Data Formats</h2>
<ul>
<li>The team discussed exploring JSON and alternative data formats like <a href="https://parquet.apache.org/">Parquet</a>, given the large data sizes in modern studies.</li>
<li>Although the industry largely uses JSON, there are concerns about its efficiency for high-volume data. Parquet, used internally by several team members, offers a promising alternative, particularly for big data applications.</li>
<li>For a comprehensive overview of the benefits and tradeoffs between JSON, Parquet, and other formats, see the recent R/Pharma 2024 presentation <strong>An arrow towards the future: A critical look at data formats for clinical reporting</strong> by Craig Gower-Page (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ipvcRPr0eig">recording link</a>).</li>
<li>The FDA has primarily used JSON but is open to considering alternatives like Parquet with further testing and demonstrations.</li>
<li>Paul mentioned he is not aware of previous efforts to convert the publically available CDISC data sets utilized in the previous pilot submissions to JSON format and then perform statistical analyses.</li>
<li><strong>Opportunity for Pilot 5</strong>: Using the structure of Pilot 3 as a template, leverage JSON as the format to assess performance. Ben Straub will draft a proposal for an initial review at the next Submissions Working Group meeting in December.</li>
<li>Nicholas Masel shared that the <a href="https://atorus-research.github.io/datasetjson/">{datasetjson}</a> R package will need updates to align with the latest schema (1.1) to ensure compatability with the future Pilot 5.</li>
<li>In addition, Nick and Ben will gather input from industry colleagues and the FDA to determine if Parquet is a viable alternative to JSON for high-volume data in future pilots, and discuss any potential technical or bureaucratic limitations with FDA.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="future-pilot-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-pilot-projects">Future Pilot Projects</h2>
<p>The team plans to prioritize two future pilot projects:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pilot 5: A repeat of Pilot 3 but using JSON format to assess package performance and ADRG requirements.</li>
<li>Comprehensive Benchmark Pilot: A longer-term pilot for H2 2025 using a large, realistic simulated data set to evaluate JSON vs.&nbsp;Parquet for performance, usability, and compatibility.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-11-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-10-04</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz &amp; Terry Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-10-04/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Amanda Martin (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Andre Couturier (Sanofi)</li>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Michael Kane (MD Anderson Cancer Institute)</li>
<li>Mike Stackhouse (Atorus)</li>
<li>Nicholas Masel (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Terry Christiani (R Consortium)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="administrative-updates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="administrative-updates">Administrative Updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>The working group welcomed Terry Christiani, the new executive director for the R Consortium. We are greatly appreciate the important leadership provided by Joseph Rickert, the previous director. More information can be found on this <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/thank-you-joseph-rickert-a-legacy-of-leadership/">R Consortium Blog post</a>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="submissions-pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="submissions-pilot-4">Submissions Pilot 4</h2>
<ul>
<li>The submissins pilot 4 (web-assembly version) was transferred on September 20, 2024 successfully and received by the FDA reviewers through the eCTD gateway transfer. The news was also shared in this <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/using-r-to-submit-research-to-the-fda-pilot-4-successfully-submitted/">announcement post</a> on the R Consortium blog.</li>
<li>Hye Soo informed that their internal reviewer computers required an update to R version 4.4.1 to match the version used in the pilot submission. She also verified that there were no issues in rendering the Shiny application with the web-assembly method of execution.</li>
<li>A small issue with column labels being switched on Primary Table was identified (a legacy issue that unfortunately was carried forward from an earlier version of the Pilot 1 output). While this is not a critical issue for the scope of pilot 4, Ben Straub shared how leveraging continuous integration / continuous deployment (CI/CD) for verifying the integrity of the data and outputs could be helpful.</li>
<li>The full review of the submission is ongoing.</li>
<li>Eric Nantz shared that the Docker container version of Pilot 4 is undergoing additional testing with the working group, and the goal is to have a transfer to the FDA reviewers in November (exact timing TBD).</li>
<li>Communication with the Nature journal on a potential manuscript is ongoing. Michael Kane noted that additional journals such as the <a href="https://www.jstatsoft.org/index">Journal of Statistical Software</a> are another possibility for sharing the concepts of web-assembly in clinical submissions.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="analysis-data-reviewers-guide-adrg" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-data-reviewers-guide-adrg">Analysis Data Reviewers Guide (ADRG)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Joel Laxamana shared the ADRG Phuse working group established quarterly meetings starting on October 16.</li>
<li>Initial steps involve identifying all of the pieces required for an ADRG, and how can templates be enhanced using the learnings from previous open-source efforts such as the Pilot submissions.</li>
<li>Additional members from the submmissions working group will be invited to future discussions after the initial brainstorming of high-level ideas.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="repositories-working-group-notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="repositories-working-group-notes">Repositories Working Group Notes</h2>
<ul>
<li>The Repositories Working Group is continuing their efforts to deliver a reproducible environment structure in which each organization can adopt to fit their needs.</li>
<li>It was recommended to invite Doug Kelkoff to a future submissions WG meeting to stay updated with their efforts</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="future-pilot-ideas" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-pilot-ideas">Future Pilot Ideas</h2>
<section id="realistic-pilot-submissions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="realistic-pilot-submissions">Realistic Pilot Submissions</h3>
<ul>
<li>The previous pilot submissions have been successful with the higher-level goals of demonstrating open-source software including R is a viable method for producing the typical submission deliverables.</li>
<li>However, the mock clinical data sets and collection of outputs are a much smaller scale than a typical clinical submission which routinely involve many data sets and clinical TFLs.</li>
<li>Bringing members outside of this core group to lead a realistic pilot submission grouup could be valuable in many fronts.</li>
<li>Paul Schutte shared that there isn’t a cononical data set applicable to the life sciences space in the way that widely-known data sets such as iris and more recently <a href="https://allisonhorst.github.io/palmerpenguins/articles/intro.html">Palmer Penguins</a>.</li>
<li>With the lack of public de-identified clinical data sets on the scale of the typical submission, creating these realistic sets via robust simulation could be a path forward.</li>
<li>Action item: Create a subgroup of those interested in this effort.</li>
<li>Sources such as <a href="https://data.projectdatasphere.org/projectdatasphere/html/home">Project Datasphere</a> are a way to obtain ADAM data sets involving treatment and standard of care data sets (with many oncology studies). One must request access before data are shared.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="json-data-format" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="json-data-format">JSON Data Format</h2>
<ul>
<li>The group is interested in learning more on the current progress of the <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/dataset-json">Dataset-JSON</a> effort.</li>
<li>Mike Stakhouse will share more information on the <a href="https://atorus-research.github.io/datasetjson/"><code>{datasetjson}</code></a> package in the next submissions working group meeting.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-10-04/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-09-06</title>
  <dc:creator>Eric Nantz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-09-06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Michael Kane (MD Anderson Cancer Institute)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Caution
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Due to technical issues, we were not able to record this session. Also, the attendees list above may not be complete. If you attended the call and your name is not listed above, please contact Eric Nantz.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="analysis-data-reviewers-guide-adrg" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-data-reviewers-guide-adrg">Analysis Data Reviewers Guide (ADRG)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Joel Laxamana is co-leading a new PHUSE working group on updating a template ADRG to account for open-source software such as R. A preliminary site for that working group is available at <a href="https://phuse-org.github.io/OSDocuMeta/" class="uri">https://phuse-org.github.io/OSDocuMeta/</a>. Note that it is in the early stages of development, but it will be updated as progress is made.</li>
<li>Attendees from the meeting interested in learning more and joining that working group are encouraged to contact Joel.</li>
<li>With the success of our previous pilots, attendees expressed interested in using a similar workflow to provide support for the PHUSE working group. For instance, Sam Parmar has already created a template ADRG in Quarto that could serve as inspiration: <a href="https://github.com/parmsam/quarto-adrg" class="uri">https://github.com/parmsam/quarto-adrg</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4-web-assembly" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-web-assembly">Pilot 4 (Web-Assembly)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Eric shared that the repository is just about ready for transfer. The tentative date for the transfer of the Pilot 4 bundle through the eCTD gateway is set for September 20, 2024.</li>
<li>Paul and HyeSoo asked if there is a desire for a small test before the transfer. Eric mentioned that from his perspective a possible issue could be access to the WebR binary package repository, which is a different repository than the CRAN repository and its mirrors around the world. Eric mentioned that there will be two different ways the web-assembly bundle can be executed:
<ul>
<li>Method 1: Utilize the pre-compiled bundle that contains the R packages as well as the application itself. In this way, the WebR binary package repository CDN should not need to be contacted from the reviewer’s machine</li>
<li>Method 2: Compile the web-assembly bundle upon first launch of the application, which will need to access the WebR binary package repository CDN to install the packages.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Eric will arrange a dedicated testing meeting for the Docker container setup and testing to see if a Docker container can be built on the reviewers’ machines.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="potential-manuscript-on-web-assembly-in-life-sciences" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="potential-manuscript-on-web-assembly-in-life-sciences">Potential Manuscript on Web-Assembly in Life Sciences</h2>
<ul>
<li>Paul requested a change in the proposed title of the paper to remove any references to “timelines.” Having any hint of that terminology could introduce additional policy issues during the disclosure process on their side.</li>
<li>The plan is to propose the manuscript for publication in Nature. It was noted that the fee for open-access manuscripts is $11,000, and we would need to explore sponsorship from the Consortium or other avenues to address that cost.</li>
<li>Eric will follow up with the editor he collaborated with on the recent Nature article <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00725-1">No installation required: how WebAssembly is changing scientific computing</a> to inquiry on interest from the editors at Nature to pursue this manuscript</li>
<li>Michael Kane mentioned that he is an editor of the <a href="https://www.jstatsoft.org/index">Journal of Statistical Software</a> and there could be an opportunity to publish a similar manuscript on this topic in that journal.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming-conferences" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming-conferences">Upcoming Conferences</h2>
<ul>
<li>Eric asked the Pilot 3 team if anyone from that group would like to join a presentation at the upcoming R/Pharma virtual conference focusing on clinical submissions. Both Joel and Ben expressed interest in joining that session. Eric will provide more details on timing and expectations once the R/Pharma program is completed.</li>
<li>Michael noted that the R-Medicine conference next year would also be a potential venue for an additional presentation.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="future-pilot-ideas-for-2025" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-pilot-ideas-for-2025">Future Pilot Ideas for 2025</h2>
<p>A key focus of the meeting was to brainstorm on potential topics for future pilots in the next year:</p>
<ul>
<li>Focused pilot on the ADRG template (more background in the ADRG section above)</li>
<li>Working with the repositories working group on a robust container image for a reproducible computing environment</li>
<li>A more comprehensive submission that closely resembles a “real” submission (e.g.&nbsp;a large number of deliverables and outputs)
<ul>
<li>A consistent piece of feedback received at previous conference talks is that the current pilots only have sparse content (only 4 tables and a figure).</li>
<li>At the time the previous pilots launched, the publically-available CDISC data was the best avenue for data</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Explore creating a large-scale mock clinical trial data via simulation methods.
<ul>
<li>On top of providing a rich source to generate many submission deliverables, this set could also be used as a robust source to test how statistical methods perform, enabling these assessments to be done truly in the open instead of behind company doors.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="additional-topics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-topics">Additional Topics</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ben asked the FDA reviewers if the approaches used in the Pilot submissions could inform a future guidance document by FDA on using open-source software for submissions. Paul mentioned that they officially will not likely make any suggestions on the use of open-source software, as current guidances are meant to be high-level and will stay software-agnostic.</li>
<li>It is possible FDA could share that sponsors should follow best practices, whatever they happen to be.</li>
<li>Paul recommended our group work closely with PHUSE who have provided best practices in the past. One potential avenue to explore is the use of the JSON format instead of XPT. Atorus Research has open-sourced a package called <a href="https://github.com/atorus-research/datasetjson"><code>{datasetjson}</code></a> to address the viewing/importing of this format.</li>
</ul>
<section id="next-meeting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-meeting">Next Meeting</h3>
<p>The next meeting of the R Submissions working group will be on Friday, October 6, 2024 at 9 AM Pacific Time.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-09-06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-08-02</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-08-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Andre Couturier (Sanofi)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Michael Kane</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>rzhang (J&amp;J)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/q1OxNGNb9yLXC8l5xAPyAdiIz9qBc5GG45Br9dVPvJAVrfpuiKWQSuNIY0QQpGSR.1wBN0XjiXC3BIVeb?startTime=1722614682000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h2>
<p>Hye Soo reported that the Pilot 3 review has not yet been completed by he FDA authorities. There are no known problems. The delay is most likely due to a summer slowdown.</p>
<p>Before the meeting Joel Laxamana shared a list of recent and upcoming Pilot 3 related talks.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>[Pilot 3 Demo : R/Medicine 2024](https://rconsortium.github.io/RMedicine_2024/Program.html)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vPmNdHTVYm8&amp;list=PL77T87Q0eoJhsC203plZ1H4p21AGrM9rl&amp;index=12">Pilot 3 Demo : useR! 2024 On-line talk</a></li>
<li><a href="https://pharmaverse.github.io/blog/posts/2024-07-03_introducing_a_ne.../introducing_a_new_coursera_course_for_hands_on_clinical_data_science_using__r..html">Roche-Genentech Coursera training on ‘Hands on Clinical Reporting using R’</a></li>
<li>Joel will also be a part of a PHUSE WG project coming up. Yet to be started, but will share more details soon.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Acton</strong>: Ning will begin a draft blog post for Pilot 3 to be posted after the FDA review is complete. The post should provide context for the achievement that is helpful for making newcomers to the use of R in FDA submissions comfortable. For example, multiple R packages were deliberately used in the Pilots in order to signal that there is no one correct way to do things.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<section id="webassembly" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="webassembly">WebAssembly</h3>
<p>Eric Nantz reported on a number of updates to the Pilot 4 WebAssembly submission package.</p>
<ul>
<li>To take advantage of the new behavior of v0.2.0 of the Shinylive package: “…when exporting an app with the Shinylive R package, or using the Quarto extension, R packages dependencies will be frozen and bundled with your app as a private #wasm package library.”</li>
<li>We have been using R v4.2.3 in the Pilot 4 submission, however because WebAssembly defaults to R v4.2.1 we have switched to this version to maintain consistency. (This will be documented in the ADRG.)</li>
<li>Making the change above also means that both version of running Pilot 4, i.e either as a traditional Shiny app or a precompiled wasm bundle, will use the same versions of R packages.</li>
<li>The new version of the Shinylive app with WebAssembly has reduced the start up time for the Pilot 4 submissions package from over a minute to 15 seconds.</li>
<li>We will schedule Pilot 4 submission for a short time after the Pilot 3 clearance is complete.</li>
<li>Because of its large size, submitting the precompiled version of the WebAssembly transfer through the FDA gateway will require an extra step of downloading a zip archive into the transfer repo.</li>
<li>Eric is now testing on Windows 10.</li>
<li>Eric will debut the app in his talk a posit::conf.</li>
</ul>
<p>When asked about how he WebAssembly will be perceived within in FDA, Paul replied that it will depend on the use case and who gets involved.</p>
</section>
<section id="docker" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="docker">Docker</h3>
<p>Hye Soo has docker installed on her workstation, and will be able work with the Docker version of the Pilot 4 submission when it is ready.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="expanding-the-reach-of-the-r-working-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="expanding-the-reach-of-the-r-working-group">Expanding the Reach of the R Working Group</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ning Leng proposed that it is time to expand the reach of the R Submissions working group to include clinicians and non data scientists.</li>
<li>She proposed blog posts and perhaps writing an academic paper noting the nature papers on
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-020-2649-2">Array programming with NumPy</a> and</li>
<li><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00725-1">WebAssembly</a>.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action</strong>: The group will pursue writing a paper.</p>
</section>
<section id="r-licenses" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="r-licenses">R Licenses</h2>
<p>There was a robust discussion about the impediment that the GPL licenses pose to the use of R that begins about 40 minutes into the video.</p>
<ul>
<li>JBR noted that company lawyers invariably seem to want to impose worst case measures when first encountering first encountering GPL licenses, and that if they do form an opinion about the limits of the license they are reticent to share their arguments publicly.</li>
<li>It was suggested that companies avoid using GPL packages</li>
<li>It was also noted that R ecosystem is mostly GPL based. An effort to track down the use of GPL licenses in packages and their dependencies included 72% of he CRAN ecosystem.</li>
<li>One apparent solution is to avoid bundling their code with GPL licensed packages, but to advise users that they should load the required GPL packages themselves.</li>
<li>The conversation settled on the notion of what is being shared, distinguishing between the code that produces tables and statistical results and code that modifies R in some way to profit from it.</li>
<li>Several members described how licensing seems to work within their companies.</li>
<li>An opinion that was offered that GPL 3 IS very “viral” but unless code was linking directly GPL2 is permissive.</li>
<li>This <a href="https://www.tibco.com/blog/2015/06/15/what-does-microsofts-acquisition-of-revolution-analytics-mean-for-the-r-language/">Tibco Blog post</a> from 2015 mentions how Microsoft was able to stay on the right side of GPL with its integration of Revolution Analytics code.</li>
<li>Also see this <a href="https://www.infoworld.com/article/2240474/sql-server-2016-gets-an-r-language-rating.html">InfoWorld Article</a> by Sedar Yegulap from 2016 which states:</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The easy way to do so and still respect the terms of the GPL is via an “arm’s length” provision. Instead of integrating the R binaries directly into SQL Server, Microsoft could invoke the R software from its own executable as needed, then return results to the host application through a file or a data stream.</p>
</blockquote>
<section id="next-meeting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-meeting">Next Meeting</h3>
<p>The next meeting of the R Submissions working group will be on Friday, September 6, 2024 at 9 AM Pacific Time.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-08-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-06-07</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-06-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eva Li</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Ismael Alejandro Rodriguez (Appsilon)</li>
<li>Jane Owens (Phuse &amp; Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Stephanie Lussier (Moderna)</li>
<li>Steven Hasendinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>YounKyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/cMcaFb0OOQmcFhdwktFrFu31Bd3ANXFm91ugZqe5WzRM0erMMzQVhYDBd1fa_Am8.ATQgpOrlYiLru6b4?startTime=1717776258000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pharmasug-conference" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pharmasug-conference">PharmaSUG Conference</h2>
<ul>
<li>Both Ben Straub (Pilot 3) and Ismael Rodriguez (Pilot 4) gave talks at the recent <a href="https://www.pharmasug.org/us/index.html">Pharma SUG</a> conference which was held in Baltimore.</li>
<li>Both reported that there was a lot of interest in their talks</li>
<li>Ben reported that he spoke to several people who thought the the FDA only approves SAS submissions.</li>
<li>Both presentations will be placed in the R Submissions WG GitHub repository.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="coordination-with-r-package-validation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="coordination-with-r-package-validation">Coordination with R Package Validation</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ismael noted that Magnus from a package validation working group approached him about cooperating with the Submissions WG.</li>
<li>JBR asked Ismael to ask Magnus to write to him and said that we be happy to invite Magnus to our meetings.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h2>
<p>Hye Soo Cho and YounKyeong Chang provided an update on their review of the Pilot 3 submission.</p>
<ul>
<li>The FDA eviewers are wrapping up their review.</li>
<li>There are no major issues.</li>
<li>They were able to install the Util package from the zip file and review the R programs to drive the ADaM data sets.</li>
<li>QC of the ADRG did turn up a minor issue regarding inconsistencies among three date variables.
<ul>
<li>The discussion of this issue begins at <strong>7:55</strong> in the video and is illustrated in the screen capture below.</li>
<li>The recommended solution is that the date origin should be specified in ISO 8601 date/time format in the ADRG.</li>
<li>Joel agreed to review the record of issues with Pilot 3 and see if there are any other parameters that ought to be explicitly mentioned in the ADRG.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-06-07/dates.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<p>Eric Nantz described progress on the Pilot 4 Submission.</p>
<ul>
<li>The end of June is still our target for the WebAssembly version of Pilot 4.</li>
<li>The plan is to do the container version at a later time after the WebAssembly version has been reviewed.</li>
<li>The question was asked if there are any special rules about package downloads.</li>
<li>Paul Schuette stated that downloading from CRAN is preferable, that in addition to the serialization FDA Security has mentioned downloads as a potential security problem, but that as far as he knows there are no regulations.</li>
<li>Eric pointed out that the Docker version of Pilot 4 also requires an image download.</li>
<li>Eric and Paul will meet to discuss this issue.</li>
<li>Eric will provide ADRG instructions and he and Paul will investigate,</li>
<li>Paul noted that the FDA has recently approved WSL (Windows System Linux)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adrg" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adrg">ADRG</h2>
<p>There has been discussion within the working group as to whether we should investigate best practices for writing ADRGs for R based submissions. JBR noted that recent comments in issue #112 suggested that we should coordinated with the PHUSE ADRG working group. Discussion begins at <strong>29:00</strong> into the video.</p>
<ul>
<li>As it turned out Jane Owens (Eli Lilly) who is co-lead of the PHUSE ADRG working group was on the call.</li>
<li>PHUSE owns the ADRG templates</li>
<li>They are actively working on updating the templates with respect to R in section 7.1 of the template.</li>
<li>Pilot 3 has documentation on R packages in Section 7 and in an appendix to the ADRG (Section 9).</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-06-07/ADRG.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<ul>
<li>PHUSE got its starting point for updating the ADRG for R from J&amp;J which Heidi Curinckx confirmed is based on J&amp;J’s participation in the Submissions WG.</li>
<li>The PHUSE WG will publish their updated template and then send it out for review</li>
<li>The Submissions WG and the PHUSE ADRG WG will cooperate and share information.</li>
<li>JBR invited Jane and other members of her WG to attend future meetings.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="r-versions-blog-post" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="r-versions-blog-post">R Versions Blog Post</h2>
<p>A small group led my Ning Leng is working on a blog post aimed at generating consensus about what versions of R might be appropriate for R based submissions at any point in time.</p>
<ul>
<li>The post has been revised to reelect the Submissions WG point of view and ends with a request for readers to comment in an issue that that we will open up on our GitHub repository.</li>
<li>The post includes paragraphs on how four companies Roche, Lilly, GSK, Pfizer deal internally with versioning and package management issues</li>
<li>Unfortunately, we must remove the quote from Paul because including it would require FDA approval.</li>
<li>Will also remove the FDA logo.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>ACTION:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Ning and the other authors will finalize the text.</li>
<li>JBR will send a MS word version of the post to Paul for final review.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="next-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-meeting">Next meeting</h2>
<ul>
<li>Because the July meeting is scheduled on the US July 4th holiday weekend and because of travel to the useR! conference the July meeting will be cancelled. * The next meeting of the submissions WG will be at 9AM Pacific Time on Friday August 2, 2022.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-06-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-05-03</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-05-03/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/YuB7-UBwkP_Dw0Ix5ofjyQEcjKF4RhbNOOyU3PqPZxRHoc0vL8NRKvPX8uUQrnrJ.BLkOTmt3skY8CjSG?startTime=1714752223000">video</a> is available</p>
<section id="discussion-of-recently-revealed-r-vulnerability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discussion-of-recently-revealed-r-vulnerability">Discussion of Recently Revealed R Vulnerability</h2>
<ul>
<li>The working group spent a few moments discussing the recently raveled vulnerability in R as reported in <a href="https://www.darkreading.com/application-security/r-programming-language-exposes-orgs-to-supply-chain-risk">Dark Reading</a> and <a href="https://aitap.github.io/2024/05/02/unserialize.html">other online</a> sites and discussed in this <a href="https://infosec.exchange/@median_headroom/112361657419172154">infosec exchange</a>.</li>
<li>The working group that the incident highlights the need for caution in accepting serialized objects just as one ought to be careful about clicking on any link from an untrusted source.</li>
<li>It was noted that our pilot submissions do not directly transmit data sets.</li>
<li>JBR noted that he has heard the R Foundation is working on an official statement about the incident and that the R Consortium will draw attention to it when it is available.</li>
<li>The working group agreed that the incident should be viewed as an “overdue wake up call” and.</li>
<li>JBR suggested that this might we a good time to see if we could attract R users with security expertise to the R Consortium.</li>
<li>Eric suggested Bob Rudis and and posted this <a href="https://rud.is/b/2024/05/03/cve-2024-27322-should-never-have-been-assigned-and-r-data-files-are-still-super-risky-even-in-r-4-4-0/?subscribe=success#subscribe-blog-blog_subscription-6">link</a> to a relevant post.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> JBR to investigate the possibility of a security focused working group.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pilot 3 was resubmitted on April 19, 2024 under BLA application number 111111 sequence 0007</li>
<li>HyeSoo confirmed receipt by the FDA and performed a preliminary analysis.</li>
<li>HyeSoo’s update begins at <strong>10 minutes, 30 seconds</strong> into the video</li>
<li>Her initial check did not reveal any major issues, but she did have a few minor issues mostly relating to the zip file and file names.</li>
<li>HyeSoo shared two solutions to the error depicted in the screen capture below.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-05-03/p3error.png" class="img-fluid"> * There was also an inconsistency with a file name in the submission and the name in the ADRG. * A solution might be to rename the file after submission. * The FDA target date to wrap up the review is early July. * This would enable Ning to include the news the the useR! presentation.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<ul>
<li>Eric Nantz begins presenting his update on Pilot 4 at <strong>32:35</strong> into the video.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://rpodcast.quarto.pub/pilot4-webassembly-adrg/">ADRG for Pilot 4</a> which is almost complete.</li>
<li>The following screen capture shows the commands starting wasm in Eric’s Windows VM.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-05-03/VM.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<ul>
<li>The 10GB threshold on etcd gateway mostly to guarantee transfer on first try.</li>
<li>Pilot 4 transfer is approximately 800 MB</li>
<li>Decision mate to try two ways of building wasm app</li>
<li>Prebuilt before transfer</li>
<li>Built by FDA after transfer</li>
<li>Specified versions of R and RStudio IDE need to be pre-installed.</li>
<li>The target for submission is late June or early July after HyeSoo has sent her evaluation of Pilot 3 off for document clearance</li>
<li>It might be possible to also submit the docker version of Pilot 4</li>
<li>Paul will investigate whether docker desktop or docker runtime is possible or preferable.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adrg-standard" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adrg-standard">ADRG Standard</h2>
<ul>
<li>There is a proposal that the RC investigate setting up a working group for drafting an ADRG standard for R.</li>
<li>We will open up an issue o the submissions-wg repository to capture ideas members may want to contribute and then discuss the proposal at our next meeting.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="recording-chat-file-contents" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recording-chat-file-contents">Recording Chat File Contents</h2>
<ul>
<li>00:08:01 Sam Parmar: Reacted to “https://infosec.exch…” with 👍🏽</li>
<li>00:10:01 Eric Nantz: This is another balanced take https://aitap.github.io/2024/05/02/unserialize.html</li>
<li>00:10:06 Sam Parmar: Reacted to “This is another bala…” with 👍🏽</li>
<li>00:11:44 Sam Parmar: The Python pickle modules has a very similar situation. https://docs.python.org/3/library/pickle.html</li>
<li>00:12:04 Sam Parmar: That blog post Eric linked mentions it.</li>
<li>00:17:11 Eric Nantz: https://rud.is/b/2024/05/03/cve-2024-27322-should-never-have-been-assigned-and-r-data-files-are-still-super-risky-even-in-r-4-4-0/</li>
<li>00:17:15 Sam Parmar: Reacted to “https://rud.is/b/202…” with 👍🏽</li>
<li>00:33:52 laxamanj: See Note from Pilot 1 submission : https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot1-to-fda/blob/main/m1/us/report-tlf.pdf</li>
<li>00:40:28 Eric Nantz: Pilot 4 Readme: https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot4-webR</li>
<li>Preview version of the Pilot 4 Analysis Data Reviewer Guide (ADRG):</li>
<li>HTML Format: https://rpodcast.quarto.pub/pilot4-webassembly-adrg/</li>
<li>PDF Format: https://rsubmission-draft.us-east-1.linodeobjects.com/adrg-quarto-pdf.pdf</li>
<li>00:52:13 Sam Parmar: Hi Eric. Did we run mention this issue? https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot4/issues/5</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="next-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-meeting">Next Meeting</h2>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM Pacific Time on Friday June 7, 2024.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-05-03/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-04-05</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-04-05/Index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Gregory Chen (MSD)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Kangjie Zhang (Bayer)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeon Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/N9uzMNTWoX-zu8M3XUliXdKO8sKEnnFlvMvUUJIjJx3oClkJBYIwDLwSXGod_uvY.OoHOPQdJMo7gelmI?startTime=1712333065000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-3-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-update">Pilot 3 Update</h2>
<p>Ben Staub provided an update on Pilot 3</p>
<ul>
<li>The Pilot 3 team is ready to make the resubmission.</li>
<li>The team will make the submission on Friday, April 12.</li>
<li>Ning will alert Bev at Roche who tests the gateway connection and makes the actual submission.</li>
<li>If all goes well, we expect the FDA could produce an evaluation report in late June or early July.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<p>Eric Nantz reported on the Plot 4 effort. (<strong>9:11</strong> into the video)</p>
<section id="wasam-version" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wasam-version">WASAM Version</h3>
<p>Eric asked for guidance on the placement of the zip file containing the application source files in the eCTD bundle. The WG decided that the placement indicated in the figure below looks fine.</p>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-04-05/etcd.png" class="img-fluid"> The ADRG will provide instructions for running the application. The workflow will be something like:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Unzip the file</li>
<li>Execute the functions provided to compile the WASM application</li>
<li>Execute the functions provided to run the application. Two versions of execution functions will be provided:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Functions to execute with WASM</li>
<li>Functions to run a normal Shiny app as in Pilot 2</li>
</ul>
<p>Decisions were made:</p>
<ul>
<li>to continue zip files for M5, and not M#, even though this may throw a low level error.</li>
<li>to keep the datasets in a sub directory of the directory containing the WASM code without having to copy them into a another location before building the app.</li>
</ul>
<p>A question was asked about what persists on the workstation when the browser is closed. The answer was: not much persists on the machine. It may be the case that some information is cached but nothing is written to the disk.</p>
<p>A question was asked about having a short cut to launch the application. The answer is that in the current state of WebAssembly it is necessary to start a new R session (or other process) that can serve static files.</p>
<p>Also note the the process that spins up WebAssebly installs the required R packages. Unfortunately, with the current state of the technology there is no way to snapshot the versions of the packages.</p>
</section>
<section id="container-version" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="container-version">Container Version</h3>
<ul>
<li>A major development at the FDA is that FDA IT rejected the request to use Podman, but recommended that we use Docker.</li>
<li>Eric will include instructions in the ADRG to setup and run Docker containers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="communication-and-documentation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="communication-and-documentation">Communication and Documentation</h2>
<ul>
<li>Joe pointed out the infrastructure developed by the Submissions working group is significant and complex and that it is difficult to explain. He asked if we should undertake an effort to expand the website to include materials to explain the processes and technology to newcomers and document the history of what has been done.</li>
<li>Ning suggested that we follow the lead of the R Valid Hub and look for a communications manager or assemble a small team.</li>
<li>Eric noted that we have been focused on the submission itself and do not want to take on the challenge of how companies might establish their internal environments. All agreed with this.</li>
<li>Joe pointed out that the fact that Ning was chatting with Doug Kelkhoff is a good sign that there seems to be sufficient communication among the working groups to keep the working groups focused and avoid duplication.</li>
<li>Sam suggested putting a start here page and time line on the webpage. For example, see the <a href="https://insightsengineering.github.io/nest/">NEST Timeline</a>.</li>
<li>Eric noted that there might be a quarto extension to do a time line.</li>
<li>A suggestion was made to compile all of our presentation.</li>
<li>The WG will open an issue on the submission-wg repository to collect ideas</li>
<li>he <a href="https://r4csr.org/">R for Clinical Study Reports and Submission</a> website might serve as a model.</li>
</ul>
<section id="actions" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="actions"><strong>Actions</strong></h4>
<p>Joe will:</p>
<ul>
<li>compile suggestions for improving the website</li>
<li>See what help the RC marketing team can provide</li>
<li>start looking for a communications manager</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conference-presentations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conference-presentations">Conference Presentations</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.pharmasug.org/us/2024/papers.html#SS-344">pharmaSUG</a> - May 19 to 24
<ul>
<li>Appsilon is planing a presentation on Pilot 4 work: SS-376 : Experimenting with Containers and webR for Submissions to FDA in the Pilot 4, André Veríssimo and Ismael Rodriguez Appsilon of Appsilon.</li>
<li>SS-344 : Piloting into the Future: Publicly available R-based Submissions to the FDA by Benjamin Straub, GlaxoSmithKline</li>
</ul></li>
<li>UseR! 2024
<ul>
<li>Ning has submitted an abstract about Submissions WG work</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Ning and Eric will be presenting at the DIA webinar</li>
</ul>
<section id="actions-1" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="actions-1"><strong>Actions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Joe will ask RC marketing to prepare an RC slide for Sam and Appsilon to use in their presentations</li>
<li>Ning will provide the details on the DIA webinar so we can promote it.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="recommended-r-versions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recommended-r-versions">Recommended R Versions</h2>
<p>It turns out that making a recommendation for the version of R for companies to used in their submissions that would best harmonize with the versions that are likely to be in use at the FDA is much harder than we anticipated. Even our phrase for identifying our recommendation “Last patch version of the previous subversion” is not without ambiguity.</p>
<ul>
<li>It is likely that each company will have its own approach to managing versions for submissions</li>
<li>Our new goal is to see if we can make an R Consortium recommendation that has sufficient industry support.</li>
<li>The FDA would like to avoid the extremes:
<ul>
<li>Submissions using very old R versions</li>
<li>Submissions using the latest R development version</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The FDA would also like to have submissions that are likely to still be available over a six year horizon. (FDA retention rules are six years.)</li>
<li>Ning proposed a series of posts from different companies on how they deal with versioning.</li>
<li>After we have published a few posts we will survey the industry.</li>
</ul>
<section id="action" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="action"><strong>Action</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ning will draft a post on the Roche approach</li>
<li>Joe will have R Consortium Marketing produce the post</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="next-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-meeting">Next meeting</h2>
<p>The next meeting of he working group will be on Friday, May 3, 2024 at 9AM Pacific Time.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-04-05/Index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-03-01</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-03-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (JBR) (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Lovemore Gakava (Novo Nordisk)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Nicholas Masel (JRDUS)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/_n7MWF0l4R5FsccL4GzRrzXUoGOCXwxQqQuY4Pu2CqF0_DX9xMmpYUoxREA92uX-.m3O3hPqvxfZKyws4?startTime=1709312595000">video</a> is available.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="plot-3-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plot-3-update">Plot 3 Update</h2>
<section id="fda-recommendation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fda-recommendation">FDA Recommendation</h3>
<p>HyeSoo stated that the FDA is considering issuing a recommendation that submissions sponsors should use the most recent patch version of the previous minor version of R.</p>
<p>For example, R versions are organized as V x.y.z where:</p>
<ul>
<li>x is the major version</li>
<li>y is the minor version or subversion</li>
<li>z is the patch version</li>
</ul>
<p>The WG members affirmed that a policy of using a proven stable version of R and not the latest version is in accordance with the practices of their respective companies.</p>
<p>After some thought the working group proposed that since patch versions are issued frequently (every couple of months), it might be better to have the FDA guidance suggest the last patch version of the previous subversion.</p>
<p>Note that the FDA is considering making a recommendation and not considering setting policy.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> JBR will confer with Sam, Paul and HyeSoo about the wording of the recommendation and then draft a blog post. The post will go to Paul, HyeSoo, Eric, and Ning for review before being published on the R Consortium Blog.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-update">Pilot 3 Update</h2>
<p>HyeSoo and Joel informed the group that they met last month to resolve the discrepancy between the original CDISC version of the ADADAS ADaM data set and the Pilot 3 version of the ADaM data set. Joel noted that there are 818 available records in the QS domain. The CDISC ADADAS only brought in 799 records and imputed the rest, whereas Pilot 3 brought in all available 818 records into ADADAS and then imputed. When the Pilot 3 team adjusted by subsetting to ANL01FL=‘Y’ records first before doing the LOCF imputation the results matched Pilot 1 and the discrepancy was resolved. Look <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam/pull/146">here</a> for details.</p>
<p>This issue illustrates the level of detail that the FDA must consider in replicating a sponsor’s submission environment. This particular issue was due to a statistical decision and not an error. Ning pointed out that most of the work in resolving discrepancies over the three Pilot submissions are due to insufficient documentation and inadequate communication and not to differences between SAS and R.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> Ning and Joe will work on a blog post about this topic.</p>
</section>
<section id="rmedicine" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rmedicine">R/Medicine</h2>
<p>Joel has been invited to give a talk at the upcoming R/Medicine virtual conference which will be held from June 10 to 14. He is deciding whether to give a talk or a workshop.</p>
</section>
<section id="user-2024" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="user-2024">UseR! 2024</h2>
<p>The group decided to submit an abstract for useR!2024 which will be held from July 8 to 11 in Salzburg, Austria. the deadline for the CFP is Sunday, 10 March at 11:59 PM CET (UTC+1)</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<p>Eric and Ning will draft the abstract.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4-update" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4-update">Pilot 4 update</h2>
<p>At <strong>38:38</strong> into the video of the meeting, Eric previews the Pilot 4 WebAssembly (Wasm) submission. To be compatible with Wasm, the submission is being built with the <a href="https://appsilon.github.io/rhino/">Rhino</a> framework for shiny which is different from what was used in Pilot 2 but is functionally equivalent. The screen capture below references the compiling the <code>WebR</code> Wasm submission with <code>shinylive</code>.</p>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-03-01/pilot4.png" class="img-fluid"> After the build it is necessary to launch a webserver process on your your local setup. The Wasm version of the Shiny app reproduces the <code>teal</code> filters without using teal itself.</p>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-03-01/KM.png" class="img-fluid"> The next step is to test the application on the container approximating the FDA Windows environment.</p>
<section id="immediate-plans" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="immediate-plans">Immediate Plans</h3>
<p>Joel’s team will continue working on Pilot 3 re-submission with the goal of picking a submission date at the April meeting.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-submission-environmnt-setup" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-submission-environmnt-setup">The Submission Environmnt Setup</h2>
<p>Setting up the submission environment is a manual process. The WG would like to automate at lest some of this process to ease the burden of setup and improve repeatability. It would be nice to have a GitHub action workflow that uses containers and runs on Azure. This will be a topic for the next meeting.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> JBR will promote this task and try to find a company willing to work on it.</p>
</section>
<section id="swissmedic-wg" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="swissmedic-wg">Swissmedic WG</h2>
<p>JBR asked the WG for help in identifying Europe-based Pharma employees who might be interested in starting a new working group focused on Swissmedic.</p>
<p><strong>Action:</strong> Ning will open an issue on this and tag JBR and Gregory.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-meeting">Next Meeting</h2>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be on Friday, April 5, 2024 at 9AM PST.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-03-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-02-02</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-02-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</li>
<li>Eric Nantz (Eli Lilly)</li>
<li>Eva Li</li>
<li>Gregory Chen (MSD)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Jizu Zhi (FDA)</li>
<li>Joel Laxamana (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Kaushal Shah (ASU)</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Renping Zhang (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang (FDA)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/dtAH375BZFxiI7SK8H5aciRvsd-8YSpCoNiUduKf9xppCitN80J2N2fZrG6A6m4V.g0LkTMFG35sCXuXj?startTime=1706893431000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h2>
<p>Hye Soo Cho presented a summary of the findings of the from the FDA review</p>
<ul>
<li>Different versions of R and RStudio
<ul>
<li>There were issues switching between R versions</li>
<li>The FDA would like the wg to explore the impact of different versions of R,RStudio and RTools</li>
<li>Also Linux vs.&nbsp;Windows</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Differences between generated Pilot 2 ADaM and CDISC data sets
<ul>
<li>attributes</li>
<li>types (e.g.&nbsp;integer vs.&nbsp;double)</li>
<li>NA vs.&nbsp;NULL</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Package and file names
<ul>
<li>Incorrect package name (pilot3utils)</li>
<li>File name change (Pilot 3.xlsx to adam-pilot-3.xlsx)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>File path
<ul>
<li>The location of a director was specified using relative file path</li>
<li>Recommendation: use full path name</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Different primary output in Pilot 1 and Pilot 3
<ul>
<li>There are discrepancies between Pilot 3 ADaM and CDISC datasets</li>
<li>Discrepancies are noted in QC findings in ADRG</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>There was considerable discussion about the challenges of dealing with different R versions and establishing a Windows test environment to test a submission before transmitting it to the FDA.</p>
<ul>
<li>The idea of setting up a gold standard windows test environment was considered but reject as beginning impractical. The actual FDA environment changes frequently because of hot fixes addressing security concerns.</li>
<li>It appears that the most practical path forward as to what preemptive measures sponsors can take to match submission environments with the FDA test environment is to work with the FDA to lock down the environment as best as can be done just prior to submission.</li>
<li>An interesting note: Paul mentioned that the FDA no longer pushes the idea of last observation carried forward for imputations. They favor exploring multiple imputation methods.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Actions:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The FDA will consider the implications of what was discussed today and decide if we are ready to resubmit Pilot 3 by the next meeting in March. The submission will use the .zip approach.</li>
<li>Joel agreed to speak with Eric about establishing an automated way to set up a container running a “vanilla” Windows test environment. <strong>Note:</strong> in a series of private email conversations after the meeting Robert Devine volunteered his expertise to work with Eric and Joel to set up the windows environment.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pilot-4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-4">Pilot 4</h2>
<p>Eric provided a brief update on Pilot 4.</p>
<ul>
<li>He will convene the Pilot 4 team to test the Webassembly submission,</li>
<li>The submission should be ready by mid March.</li>
<li>We will decide on an actual submission date in March.</li>
<li>Eric will invite the Appsilon engineers who have be providing assistance on the project to one of our meetings as we get closer to the submission.</li>
<li>The container version of the Pilot 4 submission will coordinate with the FDA to make arrangements for working with containers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="presentation-to-swiss-medic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="presentation-to-swiss-medic">Presentation to Swiss Medic</h2>
<p>On January 30, Gregory Chen presented the activities of our working group in person to an audience 15 people at the <a href="https://www.swissmedic.ch/swissmedic/en/home.html">swissmedic</a> regulatory agency and 50 people online. Gregory’s slides are in the <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-wg/tree/main/_Documents">github repository</a>. He summarized the discussion that took place after his presentation.</p>
<ul>
<li>The swissmedic audience was very interested in the use of Shiny for the Pilot 2 submission and would like to work with the R Consortium to explore the possibility of doing something similar at swissmedic. They discussed two possible ways to proceed:
<ol type="1">
<li>A Pilot 2 like project</li>
<li>Having sponsors set up a cloud environment</li>
</ol></li>
<li>The swissmedic audience said that they would prefer an industry collaborative effort rather than a vendor specific solution.</li>
<li>The were interested in learning about the resources the FDA allocated to the Pilot 2 and * asked about creating Shiny applications for market authorization.</li>
<li>The WG was excited about the possibility of collaborating with swissmedic</li>
<li>However, after some discussion it was decided that this opportunity should be pursued by a new working group devoted to swissmedic.</li>
<li>We should also find out if swissmedic has discussed these ideas with the EMA.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Action:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>JBR will work figure out how best to recruit members for a new working group focused on swissmedic.</li>
<li>This should include a call to the industry to identify people with European connections who could lead this effort.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM PST on Friday, March 1, 2024,</p>
<section id="abstract-for-gregorys-presentation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="abstract-for-gregorys-presentation">Abstract for Gregory’s Presentation</h3>
<p><u>Name of presenter</u>: Gregory Chen</p>
<p><u>Affiliation</u>: MSD, Switzerland; R Submission Working group (R Consortium)</p>
<p><u>Brief introduction of the working group</u>:</p>
<p>The R submission working group is a cross-industry working group in pharma, focusing on improving practices of R-based clinical trial regulatory submissions. Our mission is to make R-based clinical trial regulatory submissions easier today and tomorrow by</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>showing open examples of using current submission portals,</p></li>
<li><p>collecting feedback and influencing future industry and agency decisions on system/process setup</p></li>
</ol>
<p><u>Title</u>: R and Shiny in regulatory submission</p>
<p><u>Abstract</u>:</p>
<p>In recent years, statisticians and analysts from both industry and regulatory agencies have increased adoption of open-source software such as R. Compared to other statistical programming languages, R brought great benefit from its vibrant open-source community, providing a wealth of cutting-edge statistical tools and adaptability to the latest data science trends. Particularly, R shiny provided great flexibility and interactivity to increase data scientists productivity and make it easier to extract insights or review through massive statistical outputs.&nbsp;To test the concept that R language and shiny app can be bundled into a submission package and transferred successfully to FDA reviewers, the R Submission Working group (R Consortium) successfully completed two pilot submissions to FDA fully in R, and received CDER response letters (<a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/blog/2021/12/08/successful-r-based-test-package-submitted-to-fda">pilot 1,</a> <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/announcement/2023/10/05/shiny-app-successfully-reviewed-by-fda-cder-staff-pilot-2-announcement-2">pilot 2</a>). To our knowledge, these are the first publicly available submission packages that include components of open-source languages. In this talk, we will introduce R consortium, particularly its Submission Working group, and the completed pilot 1 and 2.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-02-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minutes 2024-01-05</title>
  <dc:creator>Joseph Rickert</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-01-05/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center" data-bs-toggle="collapse" data-bs-target=".callout-1-contents" aria-controls="callout-1" aria-expanded="false" aria-label="Toggle callout">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
View Attendee List
</div>
<div class="callout-btn-toggle d-inline-block border-0 py-1 ps-1 pe-0 float-end"><i class="callout-toggle"></i></div>
</div>
<div id="callout-1" class="callout-1-contents callout-collapse collapse">
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Ben Straub (GSK)</li>
<li>Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</li>
<li>Eva Li</li>
<li>Heidi Curinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>HyeSoo Cho (FDA)</li>
<li>Joseph Rickert (R Consortium)</li>
<li>Margaret Wishart</li>
<li>Nan Xiao (Merck)</li>
<li>Ning Leng (Roche/Genentech)</li>
<li>Paul Schuette (FDA)</li>
<li>Robert Devine (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Saghir Bashir (Argenx)</li>
<li>Sam Parmar (Pfizer)</li>
<li>Steven Hasendinckx (Johnson &amp; Johnson)</li>
<li>Youn Kyeong Chang</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The meeting was recorded and the <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/share/S3CjidPqOBSwSHo7xW3VUu_aUXKS9RdB3rNb07hWWkeyze5SthawUq5I8gnzQ2th.kpiljMfkqrlkuUJf?startTime=1704474237000">video</a> is available.</p>
<section id="pilot-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3">Pilot 3</h2>
<p>HyeSoo presented an update on the continuing FDA evaluation of Pilot 3.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Using the R generated ADaM data sets, the FDA reviewers were able to replicate the results of the demographic, efficacy, primary and KM plot analyses</p></li>
<li><p>The reviewers compared the results of the four analyses between Pilot 1 and Pilot 3.</p>
<ul>
<li>Primary output in Pilot 3 was different from the Pilot 1 result due to the QC findings</li>
<li>QC findings in ADRG include all of the discrepancies between the original ADaM datasets</li>
<li>The discrepancies in ADADAS data sets cause different primary analyses outputs</li>
<li>This is an issue from the CDISC ADADAS</li>
<li>It is not clear which CDISC file, the file from Pilot 1 or the file from Pilot 3, is correct.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>The following figure compares the Pilot 1 and Pilot 3 primary output. Discrepancies are highlighted.</p>
<p><img src="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-01-05/output_compare.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Comparison of Primary outputs"> Additional FDA questions included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Why is there an indication in the output of LOCF, “Last observation carried forward” when the original data set had no missing data?</li>
<li>There was no statistical analysis plan included in the submission.</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> Ben Straub will confer with the Pilot 3 team to answer these questions and review the discrepancy problems between Pilots 1 and 3.</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> Paul and HyeSoo will discuss whether we need to resubmit Pilot 3 The next meeting of the working group will be on Friday, February 2, 2024 at 9AM Pacific Time.</li>
<li>All agreed that if a resubmission of Pilot 3 is required, we will consider submitting via a .zip file.</li>
</ul>
<p>There was some discussion about what we could do to improve the quality control of our submissions.</p>
<ul>
<li>The group agreed that we should have a check list to compare items against a Pilot 1 source of truth.</li>
<li>We should have additional reviewers who are not close to the work.</li>
<li>The idea of using AI tools to check consistency was mentioned.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="upcoming-webinar" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming-webinar">Upcoming Webinar</h2>
<p>On Monday at 7PM PST Rikimaru Nishimura and Yuki Matsunaga will present a webinar on The Adoption of R in Japan’s Pharma Industry Confirmation. Look <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/r-adoption-series-the-adoption-of-r-in-japans-pharma-industry-confirmation">here</a> for details and information on how to register.</p>
<ul>
<li>Ning noted that Yuki expressed an interest in collaborating with the R Consortium.</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> we will set up a meeting with the Japanese team after the meeting.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pharmasug" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pharmasug">PharmaSUG</h2>
<ul>
<li>JBR mentioned that it is an R Consortium goal for 2024 to make the opportunity for as many speaking engagements as possible.</li>
<li>Ben mentioned that <a href="https://www.pharmasug.org/us/index.html">PharmaSUG 2024</a> is coming up in May,</li>
<li><strong>Action:</strong> Ben volunteered to submit an abstract by the January 15 deadline. Ning will provide Ben with some copy used for a previous abstract.</li>
</ul>
<p>The next meeting of the working group will be at 9AM PST on Friday, February 2, 2024.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/minutes/2024-01-05/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
